我说话清楚吗？
Yeah, am I loud and clear？
是的，好的。
Yeah, okay,
很好，嗯，
great, um,
大家下午好，晚上好，
so good afternoon or good evening
早上好，中午好，
or good morning or good night,
不管你在哪里。
wherever you are.
我们开始学习
Um, let's get started on the
6.S081 的第三节课，
third lecture in 6.S081, which
它是关于
are going to be about,
操作系统结构的。
OS organization.
今天的话题
And, topics for today
包括
are, um,
四项内容。
four things that I want to
一个是隔离，
touch on. One is isolation,
这是由
which you'll see is the driving
操作系统
design goal
设计目标驱动的。
for OS organization.
讲一下内核模式和
Talk a little bit about
用户模式。
kernel and user mode.
这是将内核或
That's a way of isolating the
操作系统与用户应用程序
kernel from, or the operating system
隔离的一种方式。
from a user applications.
然后，讨论系统调用，
Then, we'll talk about system calls,
这是用户应用程序
which is a way for user
访问内核的一种方式，
applications to basically, transition into the
使得应用程序可以访问内核服务。
kernel, so they can ask
我们看一下
for services. And we look a
它是如何在 xv6 中
little bit how it always instantiated
以简单的形式
in a simple form inside
of xv6,
实例化的，
这就是
so that is the point
今天的重点。
for today.
你还记得，
Um, and you still rethought of,
回忆一下
remind you, where we were
上节课的内容。
after the first lecture.
你脑海中的画面，
Um, the picture in your head,
你脑海中应该有这样的画面，
you should have in your head
像 shell echo
is you know there are processes
这样的进程，
like the shell, like echo.
或者其他，
or, you know whatever,
比如 find ，
find, you know, whatever utilities
无论你实现的任何程序，
that you implement, they're running
它们都运行操作系统之上。
on top of operating system.
你知道操作系统
And you know the operating system
是一种
of abstracts
对硬件资源
you know, some of the
的抽象。
hardware resources,
你知道的，
You know,
就像磁盘或 CPU 这种硬件。
like a disk or CPU,
基本上
And, you know basically the interface
操作系统和 shell 之间的接口
between the operating systems and the
通常被称为
shells are typically referred to as
系统调用接口，
system call interface,
我们一直在研究的接口
an interface that we've been looking
是 unix 接口。
at is unix interface.
我们看到的
And here what we see,
是，
um is,
在实验 1 中，
um, so that was roughly you
你已经差不多
know actually with that unix interface
使用过
you've been playing around in
unix 接口，
lab 1, um,
就是 util 实验中使用的，
were in util lab you used,
系统调用接口或
you know the system call interface
unix API 来实现
or unix API to actually implement
不同的应用程序。
different sets of applications.
所以实验 1 ，一个有用的实验，
And so lab 1, a useful
主要集中在
lab, is mostly focused on using
这张图的
you know this part
这一部分，
of the design picture
我们现在要做的，
here, and what we're going
在第一节课，
to be doing now, in
这节课，
this first lecture or this
和后续的许多课中要做的，
lecture and many subsequent lectures,
我们将真正了解
we're gonna really look actually how
接口是如何实际实现的。
the interface is actually implemented.
事实上，
And in fact almost all of
几乎整个学期都会
the semester will be spending time
把时间花在弄清楚
on figuring out, actually, how
如何实现接口上，
to implement interface and so this
这节课将是
is going to be the first
这类课程的开始。
lecture of that kind of style.
嗯，
And, um,
幸运的是，
fortunately, um,
你们中的很多人
you know, a lot of you
通过电子邮件问了很多很棒的问题。
asking really great questions over email.
或者在网站上提交了
Um, or submitted a great question
一个很棒的问题，
to the website,
我们不会
um, and we won't be able
直接讲很多细节，
to go into great amount of
在这种
detail immediately in this sort of
深入了解操作系统的
first lecture that types an inside
第一次课程中，
look of the operating system,
我们会触及
so we're going to touch on
不同的东西，
different things,
但是很多事情
but many things will become
会在接下来的课程中，
more clear
变得越来越清楚，
in subsequent lectures,
我们会做更深入地
we're going to explore in
探索。
more depth.
但是不管怎样，
Um, but nevertheless, if there's
如果有什么东西不清楚，
something unclear,
可以打断我，
feel free to interrupt and ask
提出问题。
a question.
也许
And maybe just to start off
在真正深入之前，
before actually going any further,
让我先问你们一个问题，
let me ask you a question
提问
and sort of get the question
并回答，
and answering
我要的问题是
hopefully going, and ask you like
你从 util 实验
what is the most interesting thing
学到的
that you've learned from the
最有趣的事情是什么。
util lab. And, I'll
首先，我会自己回答这个问题，
start by answering that question myself,
在完成 util 实验后，
um, one of the things that
令我惊讶的一件事是，
surprise me after writing or doing
我比以前更频繁地
the util lab is that, um,
使用 xargs ，
I use 'xargs' a lot more
我有
frequently than I used to, I
其他一些方法跟 xargs 做基本相同的事情，
had another way of doing basically
一组命令，
the same thing as xargs,
在
set of commands and after
做了 xargs 实验之后，
actually doing the xargs lab,
xargs 更方便
xargs has much
以这种方式
more convenient actually to use it
使用它。
in that way.
从那时起，
And so since then,
我成为一个使用 xargs 的
I been much more aggressive
更积极的用户。我只是
user of xargs. And I'm
想知道
just wondering what the experience has
你们的收获了什么，
been for some of you, maybe
我会点名提问，
I'll call out a few names
你们可以取消麦克风的静音来
and maybe you can unmute your
回答问题。
microphone answer, let's say,
让我们来谈谈
um, let's say a little bit
你们关于 util 实验的经历。
about your experience with util lab.
我来
Um, so let me pick
挑几个人，
some people,
嗯， Andrew You 。
um, Andrew You.
Andrew ，听到了吗？
Andrew, are you online listening?
嗯，对我来说最有趣的事
um, the most interesting thing for
是管道，
me was just the pipes,
学习如何写并发程序。
learn how to write concurrent programs.
很好，你以前
Good, have you done any sort
做过管道编程吗？
of pipe programming before?
不，没有，
No, I haven't, I've
我见过并发的东西，
seen the all concurrent stuff,
但我以前没有见过
but I haven't seen like OS
操作系统级别的管道。
level pipes before.
Elizabeth Weeks ，你觉得怎么样？
How about Elizabeth Weeks?
是的，我同意这一点，
Yeah, I'd agree with that I
我也认为操作系统管道
also thought that the OS pipes
非常有趣，
are super interesting and like the
同时也喜欢质数实验，
primes, um,
这个例子特别酷，
example specifically was cool to kind
要考虑，
of figure out and realize that
我需要关闭某些管道，
I need to close certain pipes
就像，
and just like, are they kind of
它们之间有某种关联。是的，是的，
related to each other. Yeah, yeah I remember
我记得你
you did find the pipes of
发现使用管道的质数
primes are a little bit harder
比想象的要难，
than,
它每次都让我感到惊讶，
you might thought, it surprises
完成它，
me every time, a little bit
需要一点技巧。
tricky to get right.
Jessica She.
我也认为质数练习
I also thought the primes exercise
是最有趣的。
was most interesting.
是不是
Did it take you a lot
花了你很多时间，
of time or was it not
还是还不错。
too bad.
在我意识到，
Um, it took me more time
我最初的实现不是并行的之后，
after I realized my initial implementation
我花了更多的时间，
wasn't actually concurrent so it's interesting
所以思考有什么不同
to think about like,
是很有趣的。
what the differences are there.
好的， Robert Murphy ？
Okay, how about Robert Murphy?
我认为，
Yeah, I think that, the,
我的体验是，
my experience was really just, I
我发现用原始的方式编程
found it really challenging to program
真的很有挑战性，
in the original way,
它们很初级，
it was set up so I
所以我实际上创建了一系列
actually created a bunch of helper
围绕它们的帮助函数，
functions that wrapped around things,
这就是
So that's I guess what
我所做的。
I did.
好的，还有人
Ok, any idea who have sort of
有什么好想法吗？
any piece of wisdom?
Amanda ，说吧。
Amanda, go ahead. I kind
我喜欢
of liked it and found it
并且发现它很酷，
surprising such cool, that stdin
标准输入和标准输出
and stdout are just file
用文件描述符 0 1 来表示。
descriptors themselves 0 and 1.
对，对。
Yeah yeah.
很好，
Good,
xv6 完全没有
yeah xv6 doesn't hide that from
隐藏这个，
you at all,
至少在
um, at least in a normal C
C 标准库中，
library,
它对接口
that's a little bit wrapped up
做了
in,
一些封装，
um, in an interface,
但是， xv6 没有隐藏它，
but, um xv6 doesn't hide it for you,
而是最终它
but in the end it boils
确实归结为
down indeed to know just file
文件描述符 0 1 和 2 ，
descriptor 0 1 and 2 I
2 是标准错误。
guess for standard error.
很好， Alexander 。嗯，我想，
Good, Alexander. Um, I guess,
让我感觉
um, one thing I was surprised
惊讶的，
about was also from the
也是质数问题。
prime problem.
有一个 bug
I had this bug that I
我花了几个小时的时间，
spent hours on and the thing
这个 bug 是我没有意识到，
was that I didn't realize that
每当你打开
actually they were whenever you were
一个管道，
opening a pipe and then for
然后调用 fork ，
like calling fork then basically they
那么这个管道
were be four
就有了 4 个末端，
ends to the pipe, because
因为那个管道
that pipe is kind of a
既通向子进程，
goes both to the child process
又通向父进程，
and the process the parent process,
但是我只关闭了
but I was only closing
其中的两个。
two of those.
是的，
So, yeah,
这是一个非常普遍的问题。
that was a common, common problem.
这是有道理的，
It made sense
但因为某些原因，
but for some reason,
特别是教科书上写到，
because especially the textbook says that
当你使用 fork ，
when you fork, all of
所有打开的文件描述符都会被复制，
the open file descriptors get copied,
但我没有考虑到这一点。是的，
but I didn't think about it that. Yeah,
很难，我的意思是，
it's hard to I mean
在那个接口中
there's a lot of details
有很多细节，
in that interface,
唯一真正
and you know the only way
熟悉它的方法，
to get actually really familiar with
是用它来编程，
actually the program with it,
实际使用它。
experience it.
很好，
Good good,
我希望你喜欢
well, I hope you enjoyed
这个实验，
the lab,
嗯，
um, and,
当然我也希望
of course I hope you enjoy
你喜欢后面的实验，
the subsequent labs too,
所以今天的课程，
so the lecture for today,
从某种意义上说，
in some sense is really you
部分内容是为了帮助你
know partially to help you to
开始 syscall 实验，
get going on the syscall lab,
如果你还没有开始。
if you haven't already started. And
再说一次，
so again,
你可以随时打断我
you feel free to interrupt
并提出问题。
and ask questions.
好的，我想做的
Okay, so the first thing I
第一件事是，
want to do is,
讲一下
talk a little bit
隔离，
about isolation,
你知道为什么它很重要，
um, and you know why it's
为什么我们会关心，
important and why we might care,
基本的描述是
you know the basic stories are
很简单的，
reasonable simple,
你知道我们有多个应用程序，
you know we have multiple applications,
我们有 shell ，
we got the shell,
echo find ，
the echo find and it'll
它必须正确，
be great correct,
如果你的 shell 中有一个bug，
if you had a bug in
或者你的
the shell or example in your
prime 程序，
prime program,
这不会影响
that actually didn't affect any
任何其他应用程序，
of the other applications,
特别是如果影响了 shell
particularly it would be bad, for
会有很坏的结果，
example if it affected the shell
因为当事情变坏时，
because probably the shell you're using
shell 可能
to actually kill the program,
会终止这个程序。
if something goes bad.
因此，你需要在这些不同的应用程序之间
So you want sort of strong isolation
进行某种程度上的强隔离。
between these different applications.
类似地，你知道
Similarly you know the OS
操作系统为
is sort of a servant for
所有应用程序服务，
all the applications,
你会希望情况
um, and you would like it
是这样的，
to be the case, you
如果你在某个 util 程序中
know, if, you know you make
存在一个 bug ，
a bug in one of your
实际上操作系统不会崩溃，
util programs, that actually the operating
除非
system doesn't crash, until you pass some
你把一些奇怪的参数传递给操作系统，
strange argument to the operating system,
否则操作系统会
you should be the case that
处理得很好。
the operating system handles that well.
因此，我们希望，
And so again we would like
应用程序和
to be there,
操作系统之间
strong isolation between,
进行
um, the applications and the operating
强隔离。
system itself.
思考这个问题的
Um, and one way to think
一种方式是，
about this, a little bit is
问我们
to say, is ask ourselves the
自己一个问题，
question you know what would happen
如果没有操作系统会发生什么，
if there's actually no operating system,
所以考虑一些
so you know consider some
strawman 设计，
strawman design, design,
它没有操作系统。
there is no operating system.
或者你可以把
Or you could think about it
它想象成操作系统是 [] ，
as the operating system is [],
仅仅是一个库，
just being a library,
你知道类似从
you know sort of thinking about
python 的角度考虑，
in terms of python,
可能只是导入操作系统，
maybe just import OS,
导入操作系统就是
and import OS basically loads
会在你的应用程序中
the whole operating system inside
加载整个操作系统，
of your application and that's
然后这就是
then the programming interface,
你使用的编程接口。
you use.
所以
And so you think about
你可以这样想，
that sort of way of
假设
thinking so let's say we
我们有 shell ，
have shell here,
你知道，
you know,
它可能包括
maybe it includes the library for
操作系统的库，可能有一些
the OS and maybe we
其他的应用程序 echo 。
have some other application echo.
然后你知道
Um, and then basically you know
这些应用程序，
these applications,
如果没有操作系统，
if there's no operating system really,
它们就会直接与硬件交互。
would directly interact with the hardware.
例如，
For example,
它们实际上会看到，
you know they would actually see
这有一个 CPU 内核，
you know there's a CPU core
这还有另一个 CPU 内核。
there's another CPU core.
你知道，
Um, and you know maybe there's
这有一个磁盘，
a disk and then we interact
然后我们直接与磁盘块交互，
directly with the disk blocks, and
还有内存，
maybe there's memory and they were
然后它们直接与
directly interact with the memory of
机器的内存交互。
the machine.
所以应用程序和
Um, and so there's no layer
硬件之间没有中间层，
between, no abstraction layer between basically
没有抽象层，
the applications
而且
and the hardware, and it
事实证明
turns out that it's just not
在隔离方面，
such a great design,
这不是一个好设计。
um, for isolation.
你可以看到
And you can see how isolation
隔离是如何被打破的，
might be broken,
例如，
let's assume for example that you
你知道操作系统
know one of the goal of
的一个目标
operating system is run
就是运行多个应用程序。
multiple applications.
所以，
And so,
一定会有这样的情况，
there has to be the case
每隔一段时间，
that once in a while,
它会从一个应用程序切换到
it will switch from one application
另一个应用程序，
to another application,
假设硬件只有一个 CPU ，
let's say the hardware has only
我们运行
one CPU and so we're running
shell 程序，
the shell say about one CPU,
但是
but they are periodically in
其他应用程序应该
other applications should be able
能够周期性运行。
to run to.
如果没有操作系统
Well, we have no operating system
为我们做这些，
to do for us,
那么 shell 程序
then the shell basically has to
必须
give up,
每隔一段时间
you know the
主动放弃 CPU 。
CPU once in a while.
像是一个好人，
And sort of be a nice
懂得我已经运行了
person, and say well I've run
一段时间，
for a little while, you get
现在你有机会运行了，
chance to run and there's
这就是所谓的协作式调度。
something just called cooperative scheduling.
但是它不是
Um, but it's not so great
很适合隔离，
for isolation,
例如，
for example,
如果 shell 中的某个函数
what if some function in the
有一个无限循环，
shell has an infinite loop,
那么它实际上
and therefore it will never actually
永远不会放弃 CPU 。
give up the CPU.
然后，
And then,
其他任何应用程序都不能运行，
no other applications could run
包括想要停止或终止
including maybe the application that would
shell 的应用程序。
like stop or kill the shell.
所以，
And so,
我们没有得到
um, we basically don't get
任何形式的
any sort of form of
强制复用。
enforced multiplexing.
这才是我们想要的，
That's something that we'd like to
在这种情况下，
have, where no matter what the
无论应用程序做什么，
application does, it will be forced
它都会偶尔
to give up the CPU once
被迫放弃 CPU ，
in a while,
这时其他应用程序可以运行。
that's what other applications go up.
类似地，
Similarly, if you think about this
考虑这个 strawman 设计，
strawman design, you know
我们有一个物理内存，
we have there's a physical memory
我在这里
right and all I drew a
画了一张图，
picture here,
应用程序位于
so the application sitting on the
硬件的上一层，
top of the hardware,
但你知道有物理内存，
but you know there's physical memory
代码文本和
and basically text in the code
应用程序数据
and the data for these applications
实际上位于物理内存中，
actually sits in the physical memory,
这是一个常用的内存。
it's a usual memory.
这可能是
And here's maybe you know the
shell 使用的
part of physical memory,
物理内存部分，
that's used by the shell,
这可能是 echo
here's maybe a part of
使用的
a physical memory that's used
物理内存部分。
by echo application.
所以你会再次看到
And so you're going to again
这里所看到的，
what was see here,
如果你想简单地
if you'd like simply simplistically
像这样，
like this,
在它们之间
um, there sure no boundary
没有明确的界限。
between these two guys.
例如，
For example,
如果 echo
if echo
访问这个位置，
store to location, the example belongs
这个位于 1000 的属于 shell 的位置，
to shell like location at 1000
并在那里写入值。
and writes value there.
您知道，
You know,
无论什么，比如 "x" ，
whatever "x", then it will
它会覆盖属于 shell 的
just overwrite the physical memory of
物理内存。
the shell memory.
你知道这是
And so that you know be
非常错误的，因为有了一个 bug ，
pretty undesirable, because there's a bug,
你知道 echo 实际上
you know echo could actually percolate
可能会渗透到 shell 中，
into the shell and you know
调试这类东西会
it's gonna be very tricky to
非常困难，
debug that kind of stuff, and
所以这再一次，
so this basically again, gives us
给我们的没有强隔离。
like no strong isolation.
我们喜欢的是
What we like is
有内存隔离，
to have a memory isolation,
这样一个应用程序就不能
so that one application cannot overwrite
覆盖另一个应用程序的内存。
means, memory of another application.
嗯，
Um,
所以你知道，
and so you know,
一个原因，
one reason, you know I mean, probably the
一个需要操作系统的
main reason to actually have an
主要原因可能是
operating system is basically to enforce
在复用的同时，
both multiplexing, enforce you know,
具有强内存隔离。
strong memory isolation.
如果你没有
If you didn't have an
操作系统，
operating system and the applications are
并且应用程序直接与硬件交互，
directly interacting with the hardware that
这将很难实现。
would be very hard to achieve.
因此，这种将操作系统
So this design of basically operating
设计成库的设计
system as a library is not
并不是非常常见的设计，
a very common design,
你可能会在一些实时系统中，
you may see things some real-time
应用程序之间相互信任的情况下看到，
systems where basically applications trust each
但在大多数其他
other, but in most other
操作系统中，
operating systems,
有一个操作系统
you know there's an operating system
来强制
that really enforce you know that
实施这种隔离。
kind of isolation.
因此，
So if we look a little
如果我们从这个角度
bit now, at the unix interface
来看 unix 接口。
from this perspective.
我们看到接口
Then we see that the interface
实际上是经过精心设计的。
actually is carefully designed.
因此，在复用方面，
So that actually is feasible to
在物理内存方面，
implement that enforced,
实现强制隔离
um, isolation in terms of multiplexing,
实际上是可行的，
in terms of physical memory,
其实现方式是
and the way that is done
接口对
is that the interface basically
硬件做了抽象，
abstracts the hardware,
硬件资源。
hardware resources.
在某种程度上，
In a way that then it
这使得实际做或
makes it easy to actually do
不做更容易。它使得，
or not easier. It makes it
提供这种强隔离
possible to um,
是可能的。
provide you know this strong isolation.
你知道，
Um, and you know maybe you
举一些例子，
should give you some examples,
我们已经
um, so processes we've seen
看过的进程，像是
that like things that are
由 fork 创建的。
created by fork.
你知道，它们不是字面意义上的 CPU ，
You know they're not literally a
它们对应的是
CPU, I mean, they correspond to what
允许运行计算
cpus that allows you to
的 CPU 。
run computation.
但是，
But you know,
它们不能直接与
because you know they're the applicants
这个 CPU 交互，
cannot directly interact with this CPU,
而只是进程抽象，
but only for this process abstraction,
幕后的内核
the kernel behind the scenes
可以在进程之间切换。
can switch between processes.
因此，该操作不是
So instead of having direct CPU
直接使用 CPU 来操作或
used to manipulate or given to
提供给应用程序，
the application,
而是提供
the operation provides processes, that extract
可以在 CPU 运行的进程，
away to the CPU itself,
因此实际上操作系统
so that actually the operating system
是复用的，多个应用程序运行在
multiplex, and one CPU or multiple
一个 CPU 或多个 CPU 上。
cpus among multiple applications.
同样，如果考虑 exec ，
Similarly, if you think about exec,
则 exec 提供的是内存镜像。
exec provides a memory image.
嗯，还有。
Um, and um.
阿曼达，
Amanda, yeah,
来吧，
go ahead,
问你的问题。
ask your question.
关于进程有一个问题，
One question about processes,
进程有点像 CPU 的抽象。
sort of like abstracting the CPU.
是不是
Is that
一个进程使用
one process uses part of the
CPU 的一部分，
CPU and another process uses,
而另一个进程使用该 CPU 的更多或
more, different part of that
不同的部分，或者
CPU or a different CPU,
如果是多核的话，
if it's a multi-core
另一个进程使用不同的 CPU 。
or like.
你说的进程
What do you mean by processes
而不是 CPU 是什么意思？
instead of the CPU?
好的，我的意思是将
Yeah, okay so I really mean
一个 CPU 抽象成一个进程，
one CPU abstracted away into a
所以，
process, so okay so, the way
可以这样想这个问题，
to think about it is
我们在实验中使用的
RISC-V core or RISC-V processor that
RISC-V 内核或处理器
we're using in the lab is
实际上有四个核心。
actually four cores.
所以你可以同时或者
Um, and so you can run
并行运行四个进程，
four processes concurrently or in parallel,
每个核一个进程。
one process on each core.
假设操作系统
And what the operating system does
有 8 或 7 个
is let's say you have eight
应用程序，
applications or seven applications,
它将需要一些内核和复用，
it will take some core and
不同进程之间
multiplexes, time multiplexes between
对 CPU 的时间复用。
different processes.
例如，它运行
So for example it will run
一个应用程序进程 100 毫秒，
you one app process for 100 milliseconds,
然后停止，
then stop, unload that process out
将该进程
of the CPU or out of
从 CPU 或内核卸载，
the core,
加载下一个应用程序，
loading the next
运行
application, or next process that runs
下一个进程 100 毫秒，
out for 100 milliseconds, and
它强制
it just enforces that no application
没有任何应用程序或进程
can run or no process can
运行超过 100 毫秒。
run longer than 100 milliseconds.
我们将在几节课中
We'll see exactly how this was
具体了解这是如何做到的，
done in a couple lectures, but
但这是基本思想。
that's sort of the basic idea.
好的，但是多个进程不能
Okay, but multiple processes cannot use
同时使用同一个CPU。
the same CPU at the same time.
是的，这是时间复用，
No, it's time multiplexing, you're running
你先运行一段时间，
for a while then you're run
然后下一个再运行一段时间。
the next one for a while.
好的，谢谢。
Alright, thank you.
好的，那么，
Okay, so um,
考虑 exec 的一种方式是，
one way to think about exec
它实际上是对内存的抽象。
is that actually abstracts memory.
例如，
So, for example if you
考虑一下，
think about,
exec 系统调用
um, the exec system call you
使用一个文件名，
know takes a file name,
你知道，该文件中
you know and in that file
是存储在
is basically the memory image
文本中的程序的
of a program stored in
内存镜像，
its text,
因此它是
so it's global data
全局数据，
in and that forms the
构成了应用程序的内存。
memory of the application.
应用程序可以
The application can grow
增加其内存，
its memory,
例如，通过调用 sbrk ，
for example by calling 'sbrk',
通过扩展其数据段，
extend there by extending
但它
its data segment but it
实际上对物理内存
doesn't really have a direct
没有直接影响，
aspects to physical memory,
你知道，你可以
you know you can just ask
访问
I want, you know,
物理内存地址，
addresses physical memory,
1000 到 2000 。
1000 to 2000.
没有办法做到这一点，
There's no way of getting at
同样，
that, and again the reason there's
你也没有办法做到这一点，
no way that you can get
因为操作系统
at that is because the operating
提供了内存隔离，
system means to wants to provide
控制了
memory isolation and therefore what's being
在应用程序和
controlled to intermediate between the
物理硬件之间的交互。
applications and the physical hardware.
exec 是
And exec is a sort of
一种系统调用，
system call that you know
可以捕获或显示
capture or shows that there's no
不能直接访问内存。
direct access to
这方面的另一个例子
memory. Another example of this is
是文件。
like files.
文件基本上是
Files basically abstract away
对磁盘块的抽象。
disk blocks.
比起读写
Instead of reading or writing
计算机磁盘的
the disk blocks of the disk,
磁盘块，
that's attached to your computer,
实际上，在 unix 中是
um, that actually just not allowed
不允许的，
in unix, you know the only
与存储系统交互的唯一方式
way to interact with the storage
是通过文件，
system is through files,
可以读取或写入文件，
and you can read or write
提供方便的抽象，
files, provide a convenient abstraction,
可以命名文件，
you can name files,
等等，
etc etc,
操作系统就可以
but then the operating system in
决定如何将这些文件
itself can actually decide how to
映射到磁盘块，
map those files to a disk
并且确保，例如，
blocks and make sure, for example
块只出现在一个文件中，
of this block only shows up
并且
in one file and that you
用户 a 不能操作
know user a cannot actually you
读写
know manipulate to read, write
用户 b 的文件。
the files of user b.
再说一次，
Um, and again you know this,
你知道那种接口，
you know that sort of interface,
文件抽象
that the file abstraction allows that
允许在不同的用户和
sort of strong isolation between even
甚至同一用户的不同进程之间
different users and different processes of
进行强隔离。
the same user.
正如你所看到的，
As you can see, that in
在某些方面，
some ways you know the system
系统调用接口，
call interface,
unix 接口，
that unix interface,
你在 util 实验中用到的，
giving programming with you know the
是经过
util lab, seems to be sort
精心设计的，
of carefully designed to abstract the
以抽象研究的方式，
research in way, so that you
所以你知道，操作系统
know, the operating system,
接口的实现
the implementation of the interface can
可以让多个应用程序复用资源，
actually multiply the resource of multiple
并提供强大的隔离。
applications and provide strong, strong isolation.
对这个，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about that?
在聊天中有一个问题，
We have a question in
那就是
the chat, that says do
更复杂的内核
more complex kernel try to
是否会尝试重新调度同一内核上的进程，
reschedule processes on the same
以减少缓存未命中。
core to reduce cache misses.
是的，
Oh yeah,
有一种叫做缓存亲和性的东西，
yeah there's something called cache affinity,
嗯，
um, um,
你知道现代操作系统中
you know this conversion in modern
的这种转换非常复杂，
operating systems are very sophisticated, and
实际上你知道努力
indeed you know trying to avoid
避免缓存未命中，类似的事情
cache misses, and things like that
来优化性能。
and to optimize the performance.
你们将在本学期
And you will see some of
晚些时候看到其中的一些，
them much later in the semester
在那里你们将谈论
where you are going to be
高性能网络。
talking about high performence networking.
我们会出现在那里。
We'll show up there.
聊天中的另一个问题，
Another question from chat, where in
在 xv6 中，我们可以看到
xv6, can we see how
操作系统是如何对进程复用的吗？
the OS multiplex processes?
有几个相关的文件，
There's a couple piles of files that
但 pro.c
are relevant but proc.c
可能是最相关的一个，
is probably the most relevant one,
这将是
um, this will be a topic
两三周后的
of lecture in like two or
课程主题。
three weeks.
我们将
And we're going to go in
非常详细地展示
great amount of detail and show
复用是如何发生的。
exactly how the multiplex happens.
所以，考虑这些课程
So one way to think about
是对操作系统
these lectures a little bit of
很多不同部分
an introduction to a lot of
的简介，
different pieces and,
你知道，因为我们必须
um, you know because we've got
从某个地方开始。
to start somewhere.
那么，
So, um,
我们回到
we go back into this picture
刚才展示的
here that I showed a little
这张图片，
while ago we have this,
shell 运行，
um, shell running the echo running
echo 运行
or not,
不是那张图片，
that picture,
是这张图片。
this picture.
在这边，
Here on this side,
我们有操作系统，
we've got the operating system,
我们让应用程序运行，
we get the applications running and
有一件事我们应该担心，
one thing we should be worried
操作系统
about this were that the operating
应该是，
system should be,
它应该是防御性的。
um, it should be defensive.
这是一种重要的，
This is sort of an important,
思维模式，
a mindset you know that you
你必须习惯
have to get used to one
做内核开发，
user doing kernel development,
操作系统必须确保，
um, the operating system has to
你知道的一切
ensure, everything you know everything
都能正常工作，
works out and so,
所以，
um, it has to set
它必须进行设置，
up things up so that
这样应用程序不会
you know an app cannot
使操作系统崩溃。
crash the operating system.
这会很糟糕，
It would be too bad, if
如果一个应用程序，
an application, at either by
无论是意外的或
accident or maliciously passers are tricky
恶意的传递错误参数给操作系统
heartened bad argument to the operating
操作系统将会崩溃，
system and the operating system would
这意味着服务器
corruption that basically means for denial
拒绝每一个其他的应用程序。
servers for every other application.
所以操作系统的
Um, so the operating system has
编写方式
to be written in a way
必须能够处理和解决
that it can deal and handle
恶意应用程序。
malicious applications.
特别是
Um, in particular,
另一个考虑是，
another concern is that the application
应用程序应该不能，
should not be able,
不能突破隔离。
cannot break out of its isolation.
我的意思是，
I mean,
应用程序可能是恶意的，
the application might be definitely malicious,
可能是攻击者编写的，
maybe written by an attacker and
攻击者可能想要
the attacker probably would like to
突破应用程序，例如，
break out of the application, for example
控制内核，
and take control over the kernel,
一旦控制了
and once you have control over
内核，
the kernel,
你就可以做任何事情，
then you can do anything because
因为内核控制了
the kernel is in control of
所有的硬件资源。
all the hardware resources.
所以操作系统
And so the operating system has
必须能够，
to be able to come has
必须写成防御性的，
to be written defensively,
以避免
um, you know to avoid
这类事情。
those kinds of things.
这被证明，
You know, if this turns out
要正确实现是
to be very tricky to
非常棘手的，
actually get right,
嗯，
um,
实际上在 linux 中，
in fact in Linux,
仍然有
there still
周期性的 bug ，
periodic bugs,
你知道内核 bug ，
you know kernel bugs or bugs
或者允许应用程序利用或
that actually allow an applications exploited
突破这个隔离
or to break out of this
并获得控制的 bug 。
isolation domain and take control.
但这是一个
Um, but it's just a continuous
持续的问题，
concern and we'd like to do
我们想尽可能做好这项工作。
a good job as possible.
这就是你要有的
And this is the mindset
思维模式，
you have to have, when
当你开发内核，
you're developing a kernel that
可能运行
actually applications are,
恶意应用程序的时候。
um, perhaps malicious.
这意味着，
You know, this means, that means it
应用程序和
has to be strong isolation,
操作系统之间
between the apps
必须是强隔离的。
and OS.
如果操作系统
If the OS you know, needs
需要防御性，
to be defensive and needs to
并且需要处于可以防御的位置，
be in position that can
那么
be defensive, there has to be
在应用程序之间必须有一堵坚固的墙，
a strong wall between the applications
这样操作系统
so that the operating system can
才能真正执行
actually enforce whatever policies it wants
它想要执行的任何策略。
to enforce.
这通常是这样做的，
And this is typically done, the
实现这种强隔离的一般方法是
typical approach to achieving this strong
使用硬件支持。
isolation is using hardware support.
我们在这节课中
And we get a little bit
稍微了解了一下，
of flavor of that in this
但是我们会在
lecture, but we'll come back to
后面的课中更详细地
in much more detail in subsequent
讲到这一点。
lectures. And two,
有两种硬件支持，
two part series hardware support,
一个是所谓的
one is something that's called user
用户内核模式，
kernel mode,
"/kernel模式"。
"/kernel mode".
在 RISC-V 中称为管理模式，
In RISC-V is called supervisor
但是是一回事。
mode, but it's the same thing.
在页表中，
Um, in page tables,
虚拟内存。
virtual memory.
所以所有处理器，
So all processors, sort of
某种系列处理器，
series processors,
旨在运行操作系统和
um that are intended to run
多个应用程序的处理器，
an operating system multiple applications,
都支持用户内核模式和
have support for user kernel mode
虚拟内存，
and virtual memory,
这可能表现为
you know it might be manifested
实现方式略有不同，
were implemented in a slightly different
但物理上所有处理器都有，
ways but physical all processors have,
我们使用的
um, and RISC-V processor
RISC-V 处理器
that we're using in this class
也有这种支持。
has that support too.
所以让我简单地说一下，
So let me talk a little
我要先谈一下
bit, I'm going to talk a
用户模式和
little bit about user mode,
内核模式，
kernel mode first, and then
然后我们再谈一下
we'll talk a little bit
虚拟内存。
about virtual memory.
而且大多是
Um, and mostly at the highest
从高层级讨论的。
level possible.
因为有很多
Because there's a lot of
重要的细节，
important details,
但我不能
but I won't be able to
在这节课中包含这些。
cover those in this lecture.
让我们首先讨论一下
So let's first talk about user
用户内核模式。
kernel mode.
它的意思是
And basically what it means is
处理器有
that the processor has two modes
两种操作模式，
of operation,
一种是用户模式，
one is user mode and the
另一种是内核模式。
other one is kernel mode.
在内核模式下运行时，
And when running in kernel mode,
CPU 可以执行特权指令。
the CPU can execute privileged instructions.
回到第二个[]。
Come back to the second [].
在用户模式下运行时，
When running in user mode,
CPU 只能执行
CPU can only execute in
非特权指令。
unprivileged instructions.
非特权指令，
And unprivileged instructions,
你很熟悉的指令，
the instruction you're well familiar with
你知道，
you know,
比如 add sub ，
think about like 'add' 'sub', adding
把两个寄存器加在一起，
to two registers together,
对寄存器做减法，
you know subtracting to register
所以这是你的
so it's your basic you
基本过程调用，
know procedure calls,
你的 jr ，
your jr,
所有这类东西分支，
all that kind of stuff branches,
这些都是
those are all
没有特权的指令，
um, unprivileged instructions that any
任何用户应用程序都允许执行。
user application is allowed to execute.
特权结构基本上是
Privileged structures are structures that basically
直接操作
are involved in manipulating the
硬件的结构，
hardware directly,
您知道设置保护
you know setting up protections and
之类的东西，
things like that,
例如设置
so for example setting up a
页表寄存器。
page table register.
我们稍后会谈到，
Which we'll talk about later,
嗯，
um were,
设置
you know, setting the disabling
禁用时钟中断。
clock interrupts.
所以在处理器上
So there are all kinds of
有各种类型的状态，
sort of state on the processor
操作系统
that the operating system intended to
使用这些状态，
use and manipulating that state you
你知道，
know completely,
这种状态是针对特权指令完成的。
um, is done for privileged instructions.
因此，
And so,
例如当用户应用程序
for example when a user
试图执行
application tries to actually execute
特权指令时。
a privilege instruction.
进程规则将不会执行，
Then the process rules won't
因为特权指令在
execute, because if privileged instruction user
用户模式是不允许的，
mode is disallowed and basically
这将导致控制
that will result in the transfer
从用户模式转移到
control from user space from user
内核模式，
mode to kernel mode so that
这样操作系统就可以
then the operating system can actually
实际控制，也许会因为行为不端
take control and maybe if I
而停止应用程序。
kill the application because of misbehaving.
为了理解
To get a little bit
这个，
of sense,
特权指令和
um, the difference between the two
非特权指令之间的区别。
and privilege and imprivilege instructions.
嗯，让我把显示
Um, let me switch display
切换一下。
for second.
在右侧，
And here on the right side,
显示的
you have to display is
是一个文档，
a document,
这是 RISC-V
you know the RISC-V
特权结构文档，该文档
privilege architecture document and that document
包含所有特权指令，
contains all the privilege instructions,
它是从网站链接来的。
it's linked from the website.
在 perferences 页面下，
Um, under the preferences page and
在接下来的几周或
in the next couple of weeks
几乎一个月内，
or almost months,
你会看到
you will be playing around you
所有这些特权指令，
know all these privileged instructions,
你知道，
you know,
所有特权指令都显示在这里，
are shown here and in
事实上，它们中的许多都会出现，
fact many of them will show
其中一些
up and some of them want
会在下一节课中出现，
to show up in the next
并提供更多的细节。
lecture in a great mount of detail.
但是用户认为
Um, but users think about this
这是特权指令是
as there are privilege instructions that
用户应用程序不能执行的，
user applications should not be able
只能
to execute and those can only
在内核模式下执行。
be executed in kernel mode.
这是强隔离
So that's one aspect of you
一个方面，
know this sort of hardware support
由硬件支持。
for strong isolation.
是的，
Um, yeah,
Amanda ，说出你的问题。
Amanda, go head.
我想问一个简短的问题，
Just a quick question like,
比如，
um, the what I'm imagining
我脑海中的想象是，
in my head is something
如果内核模式允许
like if kernel mode allow
或不允许那个，
else don't like what,
那么是谁在运行该代码
who is running that code and
并检查其是否是内核模式，
checking if its kernel mode,
它们如何知道
how do they know if it's
它是否处于内核模式，
in kernel mode like a flag
比如标志或其他什么。
or something.
是的，基本上是标记处理器，
Yes, basically flagging the processor,
字面上，处理器中
literally there are a bit
有一个位来表示，
in the processor,
那就是
that's just you know user
用户模式
mode,
用 1 表示，
1 is saying,
通常 1 是用户模式，
typically 1 is user mode,
0 是内核模式。
0 is kernel mode.
因此，
And so when the processor decodes
当处理器解码指令时，
an instruction,
查看操作码，
looks at the op code
如果操作码
if the op code is a
是特权指令
privilege instruction and the bit is
并且位被设置为 1 ，则拒绝
set to 1 and will deny
执行该指令。
executing that instruction.
你知道，除以零的操作，
You know divided by zero, you're not
就是不被允许。
allowed to do that.
好的，但是如果那个位
Okay, but if that bit
以某种方式改变了，
has changed in some way
你能覆盖那个位，
you were just able to
那么
overwrite that bit then that's
这是唯一可以控制的，
the only thing controlling yeah,
那么你认为
so what do you think
覆盖位的指令
what the instruction that overwrites
是什么，
a bit is that
特权指导者的非特权指令。
privilege instructor unprivileged instruction.
有什么问题吗。
Is there a question.
清除设置该位的指令
Clear the instruction that sets the
必须是特权指令，
bit must be privilege instruction because
因为用户应用程序
the user application should not be
不能将该位设置为
able to set the bit to
内核模式。
kernel mode.
正确，然后才能
Correct and then be able
运行所有类型的
to actually run all kinds
特权指令。
of privilege instructions.
因此数据是受保护的。
And so that data is protected.
你理解了吗？
Does that make sense?
好的。
Okay, yeah.
嗯，好的，
Um, OK good,
那么，
so um,
那就是用户内核模式，
so that's user kernel mode
或者至少你知道
or at least you know the
用户内核模式的大概，
top view user kernel mode,
结果是 RISC-V
turns out to RISC-V
有很多人问到的
has a number of you
第三种模式，
asked about have a third
叫做机器模式。
mode called machine mode.
我们基本上会忽略这一点，
Um, we're mostly going to ignore
我很肯定地说，
that and so I'm very much
基本上是多了一个级别，
say about it, basically it's one
因为基本上是
more level, because basically three levels
三个级别的特权，
of privileges instead of two levels
替代两个级别的特权。
of privileges.
Amir ，说吧。
Amir, go ahead.
好的，我想知道
Alright, so I'm wondering with respect
在安全方面，
to security,
如果所有的用户代码
if all user code does go
都通过内核，
through the kernel,
那么其意图
the intent is that things
是安全的，
are secure,
但是有没有一种方式
but is there a way for
让计算机的用户
um, a user of the
完全绕过
computer to completely go around
操作系统呢？
the operating system.
不，不完全是，
No, not really,
至少你知道，
at least you know if done
如果做得不小心的话。
carefully not.
如果可能的话，
And if possible like you know
就像那样，
that might be the case that
有些程序可能会有额外的特权。
some programs have additional privileges.
操作系统会
Um, that the operating system
重视的。
will respect.
但是这些特权并不是
Um, but those privileges are not
给每个用户的，你知道，
given to every user, you know, only
只有 root 用户才有
root user has certain
某些特权，允许你进行
privileges that allow you to do
对安全敏感的操作。
security sensitive operations.
那么BIOS呢？
What about BIOS, does BIOS
BIOS 发生在操作系统之前还是之后。
happened before OS or after. Yeah,
是的，所以 BIOS 是
so the BIOS is a piece
计算机附带
of software that basically comes
的一个软件，
with the computer,
嗯，
um and um,
那是先启动的，
that's booted first and the BIOS
BIOS 引导
basically boots,
操作系统，
the operating system,
嗯，所以 BIOS 是一段
um, so the BIOS is a
可信任的代码。
trusted piece of code.
最好是正确的，
And better be correct and better
最好不是恶意的。
be not malicious.
Noah ，
Noah,
说吧。
go ahead.
嗯，是的，
Um, yeah,
所以
so you mentioned that the
你提到了
you know the instruction to
设置
set the um,
内核模式位是
the kernel mode bit is a
特权指令，
privileged instruction,
用户程序
how would a user program ever,
怎么能像
then be able to you
完全拥有
know get like you essentially
内核一样，
have the kernel,
执行任何内核指令，
execute any kernel instructions,
如果就像访问内核模式
if like the very instructions to
的指令本身
access kernel mode is itself a
就是一条特权指令，
privileged instruction I guess it seems
我想应该有一个屏障，
like there's immediately a barrier for
让用户程序改变这一位。
user program ever changing that bit.
是的，这是正确的，
Yeah yeah that's correct and that's
这就是我们想要的方式，
exactly the way we want,
这是正确的，
that's correct,
所以可以
um, so one way to think
这样想，
about it,
这并不完全是
and this is not exactly how
RISC-V 上的工作方式，
it works on the RISC-V,
但是如果你在用户空间
but if you execute a privilege
执行特权指令，
instruction in user space will try
就会尝试
to execute a privileged
执行特权指令……
instruction...
我回来了，
I'm back,
不好意思，
sorry about that I look like
看起来我的 zoom 客户端崩溃了。
my zoom client crashed on me.
再次道歉，
I apologize for that I don't
我不知道为什么，
really know why,
但它确实发生了。
but it did.
大家能听到我说话吗？
Can everybody hear me again?
是的，你很好，
Yep, you're good,
一切都很好，
all good,
好的。
all right.
好吧，某个地方有个 bug ，好的，
Well there's somewhere a bug, okay,
那么回到，
um, so back to, um,
回到
back to a second piece
几乎所有 CPU 都
of hardware support which
提供的第二个硬件支持，
almost all CPU provide,
CPU 提供
whith CPU's
虚拟内存。
provide virtual memory.
我将在周三
I'm going to talk about this
更详细地谈到这一点，
on wednesday in much more detail
但基本上这个过程
but basically the process has something
有一些东西，
you know what,
被称为页表。
it's called page table.
你已经看到了这一点，
And you've seen this a little
我认为 6.004
bit I think 6.004 the
页表
page table,
基本上是将虚拟地址
basically maps virtual addresses
映射到物理地址。
to physical addresses.
其基本思想是
And the basic idea is to
给每个进程
give every process,
提供自己的页表。
its own page table.
这样，
In this way,
进程实际上只能使用，
the process can actually only use
只允许访问
whereas only allowed to access that
该页表中显示的
piece of physical memory that actually
那块物理内存。
shows up in this page table.
所以如果你设置，
And so if you set up
操作系统
if the operating system sets
设置页表的
the page tables up in a
方式，
way that um,
每个进程都有不相交的
every process has disjoint
物理内存，
physical memory,
那么一个进程不能访问
then a process can't even access
其他进程的物理内存，
somebody else's physical memory because it's
因为它甚至不是页表，
not even it's page tables,
所以甚至没有办法
so there's no way even
创建一个地址或者
to create an address or
写入一个允许一个进程
write down an address that
访问其他进程的
will allow a process to
物理内存的地址。
access somebody else's physical memory.
所以这给了我们
And so this gives us strong
强内存隔离。
memory isolation.
基本上，页表定义了
Basically page table defines a view
一个关于内存的视图，
on memory,
每个应用程序，
and every application,
每个用户进程都有
every user process has its own
自己的内存视图，
view of memory,
彼此独立。
independent of each other.
这给了我们非常强的
And this gives us very strong
内存隔离。
memory isolation.
现在我们能做的是，
And so now what we can
如果我们能以这种方式
do if we can think a
思考一点，
little bit in this way,
那么我们就能更早地
then we can redraw the picture
重新画出这幅图，
a little bit earlier and because
因为我们是这样思考的，
we're thinking about these as follows,
所以你就有了这个方框。
you have the box.
是的， ls 在
Yeah and ls sits in
那个盒子里，
that box and there's
还有另一个盒子，
another box,
echo 在那个盒子里。
when echo sits in that box.
在一个盒子里，
In a box basically has an
基本上有一个地址虚拟地址，
address virtual address range starting from
范围从 0 开始，
0 to whatever some number
到某个数字的幂。
to the power whatever
在 RISC-V 中，
number is. Um, in RISC-V, which
我们将在周三讨论，
we'll talk about on Wednesday and
同时，echo
similarly you know the address range
的地址范围是类似
for echo is something whatever
2^x 这样的。
same to 2^x.
因此 ls 的
And so ls has in
内存位置包含 0 ，
memory location 0, echo has a
echo 的位置包含 0 ，
location like a 0, and users
并且用户完全分开，
completely separated,
如果操作系统将
and if the operating system maps
这些虚拟地址 0 映射到
those virtual addresses 0 to different
不同的物理地址，
pieces of physical addresses then basically
那么 ls 不能访问 echo 的内存，
ls cannot access echo's memory and
echo 也不能访问 ls 的内存。
echo cannot access ls's memory.
类似的，你知道，内核实际上
Um, similarly the kernel actually you
位于它的下面。
know sits below it.
它也有自己的，
It also has its own, at
至少在 xv6 中，
least in xv6, has its own
有自己的地址范围。
address range.
独立于应用程序。
Um, independent of the applications.
我们可以考虑
And we could think about the
用户内核模式，
user kernel mode,
位于两者之间，
sort of sitting in between you
你知道边界，
know the boundary,
你知道实际运行的东西。
you know things that actually run.
在用户空间中运行用户模式。
In user space running user mode.
以及位于内核空间
And things that sit in the
运行内核模式。
kernel running kernel mode.
这是你应该知道的
And that's sort of the picture
操作系统的图片，
that you should actually know OS, you
你知道，
know sits there you know,
在内核模式下，
sitting in kernel mode,
所以这是你应该在
so this is the picture,
脑海中看到的图片。
you should have in your head.
正如到目前为止
Now, as described so far
所描述的，
this picture is a little
这张图片有点太严格了，
bit too strict,
你知道我们
you know we have a basically
把所有的东西都放在一个盒子里，
put everything in a box but
但是没有办法让一个盒子把控制权
there's no way for one box
转移到另一个盒子。
to transfer control to another box.
很显然，需要这些，
Clearly what needs to happen, because
因为比如 ls 可能想要
your example ls, you know probably want
调用，
to call,
你知道 read, read
you know, read, the read
系统调用。
system call.
或者 write 系统调用，
Or write system call or maybe
或者你知道的，
you know,
shell 想要调用 fork 或
whatever the shell want to call
exec 的任何东西。
fork or exec.
因此，
And so,
必须有一种方法
there has to be a way
让应用程序或用户应用程序
for an application or user application
以协调的方式将控制权
to transfer control in a coordinated
转移到内核，
manner to the kernel,
这样内核才能真正
so the kernel can actually
提供服务。
provide services.
嗯，那么
Um, and so,
这个还有一个方案，
um there's a plan basically in
除了这个，
addition to this,
我到目前为止
um, two pieces of hardware support
讲到的两个硬件支持，
I talked so far, talked about
到目前为止讲到的是
so far is a way
一种有控制的
of a controlled way of entering
进入内核的方式。
the kernel.
其实 RISC-V
It turns out actually RISC-V,
有一个指令，
there is an instruction,
这个叫做
um, for this,
ecall 指令。
it's called the 'ecall' instruction.
ecall 指令，
And ecall instruction,
它接受一个参数，一个数字。
it takes one argument, a number.
因此，当一个应用程序
And so when a user application
想要将控制权转移到
that wants to transfer control
内核，它应该
into the kernel basically called the
调用 ecall 指令，
ecall instruction with numbers like two
使用数字 2 3 或 4 5 ，
or three or four five and
这个数字就是
that number basically is the system
这个应用程序想要调用的
call number,
系统调用的编号。
that the application wants to invoke.
然后，
And then basically what that does
在 xv6 中我们看到，
and actually enters the kernel at
它在内核中
a particular point or particular
特定的点或
location in the kernel that's controlled by
特定位置
the kernel as we'll see
进入内核，
in xv6,
我的意思是在后面的一些课程里，
I mean some later lectures,
你知道只有
um, you know there's basically a
一个系统调用入口点。
single system call entry point.
而且，
And, um,
每次应用程序调用 ecall 时，
and every time an application calls
都知道应用程序
ecall, you know the application
进入内核的那个特定点。
enters the kernel that particular point.
所以，一种，
So, one,
一种方式来
um, one way to think
考虑这个问题，
about this is that if
如果你使用 fork 。
you have fork.
你知道 fork ，
You know fork,
在用户空间调用，
you know call in user space,
例如 shell 或者
for example the shell or your
你的质数程序调用 fork ，
prime program called fork, will whatever
不管什么调用 fork
calls fork doesn't really call
都不会直接调用操作系统，
the operating system directly,
内核中相应的函数，
the corresponding function in the kernel,
而是
instead you know what it does
实际上调用 ecall 。
it actually calls the ecall.
你知道 fork
With you know this number
的编号。
for fork.
然后它会
And then that actually jumps into
跳转到内核。
the kernel.
所以这是一个内核转换。
So this is a kernel transition.
这是用户端，
And here's the user side, here's
这是内核端，
kernel side, and then on
然后在内核端，
the kernel side,
你知道在 syscall.c 中
you know there's a function called
有一个名为 syscall 的函数，
syscall in syscall.c and
然后每个系统调用都会在
then basically every system call will
那个特定的系统调用函数结束，
end up at that particular system
系统调用
call function, and the system call
会查看这个数字，
will look at the number and
然后决定在寄存器中
then decide and the numerous action
传递的大量操作，
passed in register I think it's
我想它是 a0 。
a0.
嗯，去看看
Um, and just go and
那个寄存器，
look at that register look
看看 a0 ，
at a0, see what the
看看数字是多少，
number is and then,
比如调用 fork
for example called the fork
系统调用。
system call.
为了明确一下，
Um, and so just to make
这是用户和内核之间的
clear so this is this hard
硬边界，
boundary between the user and kernel,
所以用户不能调用，
so the user cannot call,
你知道这个 fork 直接，
you know this fork directly,
你知道用户应用程序
you know the only way user
实际调用系统调用 fork
application can actually invoke the system
的唯一方式是通过
call fork is actually through this
这个 ecall 指令。
ecall instruction.
我们还有另一个，
And so we have another, um,
如果我们有另一个，
if we have another, um,
另一个系统调用，
another system call let's
比如 write 。
say write.
它做了一些类似的事情，
It does something similar,
你知道 write 系统调用
you know the write system
不能直接调用
call cannot call you know the
内核中的
write, you know code directly into
write 代码，
the kernel,
相反，它所做的，
instead, um what it does,
它调用
it calls what's these little wrappers
小包装器，
are called,
系统调用停止，
system call stops it will call
它会调用 ecall。
ecall.
以及一个名为 write 的函数，
And function called write that actually
它实际执行 ecall 指令，
executes ecall instruction with the argument
参数为系统调用 write ，
you know syscall write,
以指示 write 系统调用，
to indicate the write system call,
然后再次将控制权
and then again transfer control to
转移给 syscall 。
syscall.
然后 syscall ，
And then syscall,
可以分配
um, can actually demultiplex
到 write 系统调用中。
into the write system call.
有两个问题，
There are two questions,
请继续提问。
please go ahead.
所以，我想我们
So, I think my hands up
都举手了。
both.
好的，我可以先提问。
Okay I can go ahead.
我的问题是，
Oh, the question I had was,
内核如何或
um, how does or where does
在哪里检查，
the kernel check,
嗯，
um, for,
比如 fork 或 write ，
for example fork or write, if
是否允许或不允许。
it is allowed or not.
嗯，现在，
Um, right now,
你只是传入，
you're just passing in, like you
就像你只是在调用 ecall 和
know you're just calling ecall
系统调用号，
and the system call number,
但是内核决定
but where does the kernel
这个应用程序
basically decide whether this application
是否应该能够调用
should be able to invoke
这个特定的内核系统调用。
this particular kernel syscall.
是的，这是一个好问题，
Yeah, so a great question,
原则上，你知道
so in principle you know on
在内核方面是正确的，
the kernel side correct, when we
当我们使用 fork 调用运行的时候。
actually use fork call runs.
它可以实现它想要的
Um, it can implement any
任何安全检查，
secure check
你可以查看系统调用的参数，
it wants, you could look at
然后决定
the arguments if the system call
是否应该
and decide whether actually the application
允许应用程序
should all be allowed to execute
执行系统调用 fork 。
the system call fork.
在用户中，或者在 unix 中，
Now in user or in unix
或者任何应用程序中，都可以调用 fork ，
or any application can actually call
但是让我们假设 write 。
fork but let's say take write.
你知道， write ，
You know write,
你需要检查 write 的
you need to check whether
实现是否需要检查，
the implantation of write needs to
传递给 write
check, whether the address that is
的地址
actually passed into write, actually is
是否是用户应用程序的一部分。
part of the user applications.
所以
Um, and so that you
内核从其他地方写入数据
know the kernel is not
是不正确的，
correct to writing data
它实际上
from somewhere else, it actually
不属于应用程序。
doesn't belong to the application.
还有更多的线索，
There more
你知道的。请提问。
hints, you know. Please ask.
嗯，我有一个
Um, yeah I had a
简短的问题，
quick question,
在用户应用程序
um, so how did the
恶意或无限循环的情况下，
kernel seize back control from a
内核是如何
user application in the case where
从用户应用程序手中
the user application is acting maliciously
夺回控制权的。
or in an infinite loop.
是的，方式是，计划是，
Yeah, so the way the plan
我们将
for that and again we're going
在几周内
to talk about in much more
再次详细讨论，
detail in a couple weeks,
内核实际上
um is that the kernel
是编程的，
actually programs,
使用硬件的
the hardware to a set
定时器。
of timer.
而在计时器关闭之后，
And after the timer goes off,
会导致从用户空间到
um, that will cause a transfer
内核模式的转换，
from user space to kernel mode,
在这一点上内核又
at that point the kernel is
回到了控制之中。
back in control.
然后内核可以将 CPU
And then the kernel can reschedule
重新调度到另一个进程。
the CPU to another process.
好的，有道理，谢谢。是的，
Okay makes sense, thank you. Yeah we'll
我们会看到确切的细节，
see the exact details you know
我们会
we'll see,
在一段时间内看到。
um, in a little while.
我们还有更多的问题要问。
We have more questions.
是的，
Yeah, so this is more of
这是一个更高层次的问题，
a high-level question,
是什么驱使操作系统
but what drives the designers of
实现的设计者
an operating systems implementation to use
使用像 C 这样的语言呢？
a language like C?
嗯，
Um, um,
好的，很好的问题，
okay, so great question,
C 语言给了你
um, C gives you a lot
对于硬件的
of control,
很大的控制权。
um over hardware.
还有，
And, um,
那么，
so, um,
举个例子，
for example,
你知道你需要
you know you need to program
对计时器芯片进行编程。
the timer chip.
在 C 语言中，
Um, and um in C that
这很容易做到，
is actually easy to do,
因为你可以对任何硬件资源
because you get a lot of
进行很多低级控制，
low-level control over any hardware resource
部分原因是你可以将任何东西
and partly because you can cast
强制转换为任何东西，
anything to anything,
所以，
um, and,
C 语言是非常
um, so C is basically very convenient
方便的语言，
programming language,
如果你必须
if you have to move
进行非常低级的编程，
very low-level programming and particularly
特别是与硬件交互。
interacting with hardware.
这并不意味着
It doesn't mean you can't do
你不能用其他语言来做，
it in other languages,
但是这是历史上
um, but this is historically the
C 语言成功的原因。
reason why C has been successful.
我明白了，
I see,
谢谢。为什么我看到
thanks. Why I see so much
像这些类型的应用程序
more popular than c++
这样的历史原因比 C++
only for historic reasons in like
流行得多，或者，
these kinds of applications or um,
大多数操作系统
is there any other reason that
没有采用 C++
like, like most OS don't
还有其他原因吗？
have adopted C++.
是的，大多数操作系统，
Yeah, so most operating system,
我认为使用 C++
there are I think operating
编写操作系统
systems written in C++
是完全可能的，
totally possible,
可能是你知道的，
probably the most ones that you
你知道的大多数操作系统
know, you know are not written
都不是用C++写的。
in C++.
还有各种原因，
Um, and the various reasons for,
你知道，linux 大部分
you know, Linux is mostly
是 C 而不是 C++ ，
C or no C++
我想部分原因是 Linus
and I think partially because Linus
不喜欢 C++ 。
just doesn't like C++.
还有其他问题吗？
Any other questions?
好的，那么，
Okay, so, so in this view
在这个世界观中，
of the world,
你知道我们有一种方法
were you know we have a
可以通过系统调用或 ecall 指令
way of transferring control into
将控制权转移到
the operating system using system calls
操作系统中，
or the ecall instruction and
并且内核不负责
there's a kernel is not responsible
实际实现函数，
for implementing actually the actual functions
并确保检查参数
and ensuring checking arguments and
之类的东西，
things like that to make sure,
确保操作系统
that you know that,
不会被骗
Um, it's not being tricked
做了什么，
into something,
做一些坏事，
um doing something badly and so
所以在这个世界观里，
in this view of the world,
内核有时被称为，
the kernel is sometimes called,
你知道，
you know,
这是可信任的计算基础。
it's the trusted computing base.
在安全术语中有时
Sometimes called in security terms
被称为TCB。
the TCB.
你知道
Um, and basically you know what
作为可信计算基础
does it mean to be the
意味着什么，
trusted computing base,
它必须是正确的，
well it must be correct, kernel
内核必须没有错误。
must have no bugs.
因为如果内核里
Because if there's a bug in
有个 bug ，
the kernel,
你知道
you know the way to think
怎么想，
about it,
这个东西，
this stuff,
也许攻击者能够
maybe an attacker is able to
利用这个 bug ，
to [tickle] the bug and
把 bug 变成一个漏洞。
turn the bug into an exploit.
可能会允许
And you know that exploit may
特定的攻击者
be allowed a particular attacker to
打破隔离或者
break out of isolation or maybe
控制内核，
take control over the kernel,
所以你知道
and so it's really important
内核必须有
that you know the kernel
尽可能少的错误，
really has to have as
这一点非常重要。
few bugs as possible.
看不见的内核，
Invisibly the kernel,
你必须将，
you must treat,
将用户应用程序
treat user apps or applications
或进程
or processes
视为恶意代码。
as malicious.
就像我之前说的，
Basically as I said before, []
内核设计者应该有一种
the kernel designer should have
安全的思维模式，
a security mindset,
在你编写和
um, you know when writing and
实现内核代码的时候。
implementing a kernel code.
实现这个目标
In, in its heart to
的关键是，
achieve this goal,
我们没有 bug ，
we have no bugs,
如果你的操作系统非常大，
if your operating system gigantically big,
不是那么简单的，
is not that straightforward and
几乎每个操作系统，
almost every operating system,
你知道用户广泛使用的，
you know the user is widely
有时有
used, once in a while
一个安全漏洞，
actually has a security bug and
它们会随着时间的推移得到修复。
they get fixed over time.
但是，
But basically,
不管怎样，
no matter what, there's always a
在某一环节总会有新的漏洞出现，
new exploit at some point down
以后你就会明白
the line, and you will see
为什么把它做好
later why it's so tricky to get
是如此的困难，
it all and right,
但是你应该能理解，
um, but you know the sort
内核必须
of understandable like the kernel has
做困难的事情。
to do tricky stuff.
它必须操作硬件，
It has to manipulate hardware,
它必须
um, it has to be
非常小心地检查，
very careful in it's checking
它很容易
it's very easy to make
犯一个小错误，
a small slip up and
就是一个 bug 。
you know have a bug.
所以，
And so,
个即时的问题就是
instant question is then what
什么应该在内核模式下运行，
should run in kernel mode because
因为内核代码实际上
it's really the kernel code actually
是在内核模式下运行的，
is in kernel mode that is
这是敏感代码，
the sensitive code that is
也就是可信计算的时代。
the trusted computing days.
这个问题的
Um, and one answer to that
一个答案是，
question is like,
我们有自己的
well you know we have our
用户内核边界，
user kernel boundary,
这是用户，
so here's user,
这是内核。
here's kernel.
用户应用程序运行，
A user applications running,
这里的程序运行在
and here is the program running
内核模式下，
in kernel mode,
一种选择是将整个操作系统
one option is to stick the
置于内核模式。
whole operating system in kernel mode.
例如，
For example,
在大多数 unix 操作系统中，
in most unix operating systems,
整个 unix 实现都
the whole unix implementation runs inside
在内核模式内运行。
of kernel mode.
因此，在 xv6 中，
So in the xv6,
所有操作系统服务
all the operating system services are
基本上都处于内核模式，
basically in kernel mode,
这被称为
and this is called monolithic
宏内核设计。
kernel design.
你知道
And you know there there's
可以从几方面
couple things in the way to think
来考虑这个设计。
about it.
一方面，它可能对 bug
One way, it's probably not so good
不太友好。
for bugs.
因为在宏内核设计中
Because any bug you know that
任何 bug 实际上
you might have in a monolithic
都可能变成一个漏洞，
design might actually turn into an
这是不好的，
exploit and that would be bad,
我们有一个
um, so we have a
在内核中运行的
large operating system running inside
大型操作系统，
of the kernel,
它们可能会有
it's likely they're going to be
更多的 bug ，
more bugs,
但任何可以查询到
but any statistics that can
的统计数据，
look up who says like
比如每几千行代码，
every few thousand lines of
都会有
code will have you know
一些 bug 。
some small number of bugs.
所以如果你有
And so if you have many,
更多的代码
many more lines of code running
在内核中运行，
in the kernel block,
你知道的，你有
you know, the probability the chance that
有这样的机会。
you have.
然后巨大的 bug
Um, and then huge bug
会增加一点，
goes up a little bit
所以
and so downside from the
从安全的角度来看，
monolithic kernel design from a
宏内核设计的缺点
security perspective is that there's a
有很多代码
lot of code in the
在内核中。
kernel.
不过，好处是
Um the plus though is
你知道的，
you know,
通常，如果你考虑一个
typically, if you think about an
包含各种不同部分的
operating system that contains all kinds
操作系统，
of different pieces,
可能有
you know you might have
文件系统部分。
file system piece.
可能有
You might have the virtual
虚拟内存部分，
memory piece,
可能有进程，
um, you might have processes
你知道的。
you know.
因此，操作系统内部
And so there are all kinds
有各种实现特定功能的
of sub modules inside of the
子模块。
operating system that implement particular functionality.
好的一面是
And the plus side of
会有
that is there's going to
紧密的整合。
be tight integration.
在这些不同的子模块之间，
Possible between these different sub modules,
如果它们都在
if they're all sitting in the
同一个程序中。
same program.
这种联系会带来
And that connection leads to
很好的性能。
great performance.
举个例子，
An example if you look at
如果你看 linux 操作系统，
an operating system Linux,
它实际上实现了
it actually achieves a very
非常令人印象深刻的性能。
impressive performance.
有一种，
Um, and so there's a one,
一种设计，另一种设计
one design, another design
主要集中在
which basically focuses on reducing the
减少内核中的代码量，
amount of code in the kernel
这就是所谓的微内核设计。
is what's called micro kernel design.
在这个设计中，
And in this design,
你的目标是
your goal is actually to run
在内核模式下
as few lines as possible in
运行尽可能少的代码，例如，
kernel mode and for example there
通常有一些东西是内核的。
is something often kernel.
但是内核只包含
But the kernel has very few,
很少的组件，
um, components to it,
所以通常有
so general typically has some form
某种形式的 IPC 或消息传递。
of IPC or message passing.
少量的虚拟内存支持，
A little bit of vm support
非常少。
very minimal.
基本上，只有页表和
Basically, only thing necessary for page
复用 CPU 的
tables and something to multiplex
一些东西，
different CPUs,
一些复用代码。
so, some multiplexing code.
但通常我们的目标是
But generally the goal is to
[阻止]内核外
[prevent] the bug of the operating
操作系统的 bug ，
system outside of the kernel,
例如，
and so for example again, as we
由于我们在这里有自己的边界，
have our boundary here,
我们要做的实际上是
um what we'll do is actually
我们将内核的其他部分
we'll run other parts of the
作为普通用户应用程序来运行，
kernel as normal user applications,
例如，我们可能有，
for example we might have,
可能有一个用户进程，
you might have a user process,
仍然不是有意的，但没关系，
still not intended but doesn't matter,
我刚刚做的
you know I just did
文件服务器。
file server.
然后，
And so and then the
文件服务器，
file servers,
只是普通的用户空间。
just regular user space.
用户空间内核，
User space kernel,
即使我
so even though I drew,
不小心
by accident,
画了红色的，
in red, I intended to draw out
我打算画黑色的，文件服务器运行用户应用程序，
in black, the FS are mine, running
你知道，就像 echo 一样。
user application like, you know, echo.
你知道 shell ，
You know the shell,
它们都在用户空间中运行，
they're all running in user space
我们可能会有其他用户应用程序，
and we might have other user
比如虚拟内存系统的某些部分
applications like parts of the vm
实际上可能会在
system might actually run the regular
用户模式下运行
user application
常规用户应用程序。
in user mode.
所以这是一个
And so this is sort of
很好的设计，
a nice design,
因为在内核中的
because the amount of code
代码量
that presumably that's in the
很小。
kernel is small.
这是很小的方法，
It's small and small means,
希望更少的 bug 。
hopefully fewer bugs.
当然，有一个问题，
The one issue of course is
我们必须
like you know we have to
安排 shell 可以
arrange that shell can talk to
访问文件系统，例如，
the file system, for example,
shell 调用 exec ，
the shell calls exec and there
并且必须有一种
has to be a way of
访问文件系统的方法。
getting to the file system.
因此，通常
And so typically the way
它的工作方式是
it works is that the
shell 通过
shell will send a message
IPC 系统
through the IPC system
向内核发送消息。
to the kernel.
内核会看着，
The kernel will look at and
你知道
say like, oh you know this
这是针对文件系统的，
is intended for the file systems
对文件系统
and file systems and sensitive to
很敏感。
the file system.
文件系统为它工作。
The file system does for work.
会发回一条消息，
You know sends a message back
告诉你，
saying you know,
这是 exec 系统调用
here's the results of your exec
的结果，
system call and then you send
然后将其发送回 shell 。
it back to the shell.
因此，
And so,
这些通常是使用
um, these are typically implemented
消息来实现的。
using messages.
所以对于与文件服务器的
Um, and so for any interaction
任何交互，
with the file server,
现在必须跳入内核一次，
now you have to jump once into
跳出内核一次，
the kernel, once out of the kernel, once
再跳入内核一次，
into the kernel,
再跳出内核一次。
once out of the kernel.
如果你将其与
If you compare that with
之前的设计进行比较，
the previous design like if
例如，如果想要
this guy wants to talk
访问文件系统，
to the file system,
只需一次系统调用和
it's one system call in and
一次调用返回。
one basically call back out.
因此，系统调用条目的数量
And so you double the number
翻了一番。
of a system call entries.
因此，提供微内核方法的
And so, one typical problem
一个典型问题或挑战
or challenge,
实际上
with offer the micro kernel approaches
是如何
is actually how to achieve
获得良好的性能。
good performance.
它有两个
And it has sort of two
部分组成。
components to it.
你知道，
Um, you know just jumping back
在用户模式和内核模式之间来回切换
and forth between user mode and
才能完成一些事情，
kernel mode to actually get something
第二部分是
done and the second part is
因为不同的部分
because you know the different pieces
彼此之间很好地隔离，
are really well isolated from each
紧密集成较少，
other a tight integration is less,
调度起来
you know more complicated to arrange
比宏内核更复杂，
than for example in the monolithic
在宏内核中，
kernel, where basically everybody can,
虚拟内存系统中的文件系统
the file system in the virtual
可以很容易地
memory system can easily share a
共享页面缓存，
page cache which a little bit
这在微内核设计中比较难实现，
harder to achieve in the micro
还有有时更难
kernel design and therefore it's sometimes
获得高性能。
more difficult to get high performance.
微内核和宏内核之间的这些区别
Now these distinctions between micro
是非常高层级的。
and monolithic very high-level.
所以在实践中，
So in practice,
这两种类型的内核设计
both types of kernel design
都出现了，由于历史原因，
show up, most desktop operating
大多数桌面操作系统
systems are typically monolithic systems,
都是典型的宏内核系统。
motion for historical reasons.
如果你运行
A lot of the if you
操作系统密集型
run a very intense you know
应用程序，
OS intense applications for example in
例如数据中心，
the data center,
它们通常运行在宏内核上，
they typically run on a monolithic
这主要是因为
kernel, mostly because linux
linux 提供了很好的性能。
provides great performance.
但许多，
But many, for example, embedding settings
例如， minix 或 [cell4] 这样的嵌入式系统，
like minix or [cell4], those tend
往往是微内核设计。
to be micro kernel designs.
所以这两种设计都很流行，
And so both designs are popular,
你也可以从头开始设计
um, you could probably start a
一个新的操作系统。
new operation system from scratch.
你可能会从，
Um, you probably start with,
你知道，
you know, you may start
你可能会从微内核设计开始。
with a micro kernel design.
一旦你有了 linux 这样的
Once you have a monolithic
宏内核设计，
design like for example Linux,
重写微内核设计的
it's going to be would
任何东西都
be a ton of work
将是一项
to rewrite anything to a
繁重的工作，
micro kernel design as maybe
因为不利于
not conducive to the incentives
人们可能想要花时间
people probably want to spend
来增加新功能，
rather time including new features
而不是真正地
than actually,
重新设计内核。
restructuring the kernel
嗯，
Um, so,
这是两种主要的设计，
these are sort of two main designs,
正如你知道的， xv6
um, as you know xv6 is
属于宏内核设计，
falls into monolithic design is
这是经典的 unix 系统所做的，
most classic unix systems do,
但在本学期晚些时候，
but later in the semester,
我们会更详细地
um, we'll talk a lot more
讨论一些
in detail about some of the
微内核设计。
micro kernel designs.
对这个有什么问题吗，
Any questions about this because this
因为这是电子邮件问题列表中的
was a hot topic in the,
热门话题。
in the email of questions.
好的，
Um, okay,
让我转换一下。
let me switch little bit.
我将转到
I'm going to get to some
一些代码，看看这
code and see how this plays
在 xv6 中是如何运行的。
out in xv6.
嗯，我们这里有两个窗口。
Um, so we're here two windows.
你知道， emacs ，
Um, and you know, emacs, you
你知道的，就像 proc 结构。
know with like the proc structure.
我想做的
Um, and the first thing I
第一件事是，
wanna do is,
你稍微看一下代码库，
um, you look a little bit
你可能
at the code base, you've
已经这样做了，
probably already done this,
但你会看到代码
but you see that the code
是按照三个部分
is sort of organized along three,
组成的。一个是 kernel ，
three parts. One the kernel,
你知道，kernel
and you know kernel that basically
包括所有内核文件，
includes all the kernel files xv6
xv6 是一个宏内核，
being a monolithic kernel,
所有这些程序都被编译成
basically all these programs are compiled
一个称为 kernel 的二进制文件，
into a single binary called the
这实际上就是
kernel and that's actually what you
你在内核模式下运行的。
run in kernel mode.
然后，有 user ，
Um, and then you know there's
这些基本上都是在
user and those are basically the
用户模式下运行的程序，
programs that run in user mode,
这就是为什么
and this is why you're going
一个叫做 kernel ，
to, one is called kernel and
另一个叫做 user 。
the other called user.
然后还有一个叫 mkfs
And then there's one more program
的程序，
called 'mkfs',
它实际上构建了一个
um, which actually builds an
空文件系统映像，
empty file system image that we've
我们将其存储在磁盘上。
stored on disk.
嗯，这样我们就可以
Um, so that we can get
从一个空的文件系统
off the ground with an empty
开始。
file system.
好的，在此之前，
Okay so before so you switch
再次切换到，
back again to I want to
我想说一下内核
say a little bit about how
是如何编译的。
the kernel is compiled.
因为你可能已经看过了，
Um, because you probably have seen
但可能没有真正意识到，
this and you might not really
所以了解一下
have realized it, it's important
是很重要的。
to understand.
所以当内核，
Um, so when the kernel,
内核的构造，
the construction of the kernel,
makefile 使用
the makefile basically takes one
这些 C 文件中的一个，
of these C files like
比如 proc.c 。
proc.c.
你知道，
You know invokes you know
调用 GCC ，
the GCC,
GCC 编译器，它生成
the GCC compiler that generates a
一个名为 proc.S 的文件。
file called proc.S.
这是类似的。
That goes to the similar.
这是
And this is basically
RISC-V 组件。
RISC-V assembly.
这实际上会产生一个
And that actually produces a
文件 proc.o ，
file proc.o,
基本上就是
and basically that's you know
汇编程序的二进制版本。
the binary version of the assembler.
你知道 makefile
Um, and you know the makefile
执行这个规则，
does this rule, you know
你知道 kernel 中的部分文件，
part files in the kernel,
比如 pipe 。
so example, pipe.
还有一个你知道的，
Another one you know,
跟 GCC 编译成
same story GCC compiles to
pipe.S 类似。
pipe.S.
你知道，经过类似的过程，
And you know go to through
我们会得到 pipe.o 。
similar and we get pipe.o.
然后是加载器，
And basically then the loader,
它接受所有这些 .o 文件。
it takes all these .o files.
从所有不同的文件中，
From all the different you know
并将它们链接在一起，
files and links them together and
然后产生内核。
produces, produces the kernel.
就像我们实际
And as actually then what
运行的那样。
we run.
为了方便起见，
And you know, for your convenience,
makefile 还会生成
you know the makefile
一个名为
also produces a file called
kernel.asm 的文件。
kernel.asm.
它有完整的内核，
That has the complete kernel,
反汇编代码，
disassembled and you can just look
你可以查看它，
at it and you know that
当你有内核 bug 时，
helps later on when you have
这会有帮助，
kernel bugs and it's easy to
很容易看出哪条指令，
see which instruction,
在你得到 bug 的时候
um, was executed at the point
执行的。
you got the bug.
举个例子，
As an example if I,
如果我在这里， kernel.asm 。
here, kernel.asm.
嗯，我们看到，
Um, we see,
这是 kernel 文件，
um, here's the kernel file
如果您发送指令的话。
if you send instructions.
而且，你知道的，
And, um one thing you know,
比如，第一行
for example is the first.
指令位于
instruction is located at
该地址 80000000 ，
this address 80000000
并且
and
这是 auipc 指令
that is whatever
RISC-V 的指令。
auipc instruction RISC-V instruction.
嗯，
Um,
有人知道这是什么吗，
anybody knows what this is,
0000a117 ， 83010113 ， 6505 ，
0000a117, 83010113, 6505,
有人想回答这个问题吗？
Anybody want to answer that
右边是十六进制版
question? That's the hex version of
的汇编指令。
the assembly instructions on the right.
没错，
Yeah exactly,
0000a117 上的符号和
so what here on the 008117
文本的 auipc 的
is exactly the same
符号是
thing as symbolic you know
完全一样的，
the textual version of that,
所以这是
aupc and so basically
实际指令的
this is the binary encoding of
二进制编码。
the actual instruction.
所以，每条指令
So, and every instruction has a
都有一个二进制编码，
binary encoding and you know the
你知道 kernel.asm 文件实际上
kernel.asm file actually
显示了这些二进制编码。
shows those binary encodings.
这有时很方便，
And this is sometimes convenient,
当你查看 gdb
when you look at gdb and
并想知道
you want to know what actually
实际发生了什么时，
is going on,
您可以看到实际的
you can see actually what the
二进制编码是什么。
binary encoding is.
好的，那么当我们
Okay, so then when we run
运行 xv6时，
xv6, I'm going to run
让我先在
on the inside actually let me
没有 gdb 的情况下运行。
first run it without gdb.
你知道的，
Um, you know compile a
编译一堆东西，
bunch of stuff and then
然后调用 QEMU 。
invokes QEMU.
这是一个明显的
And this is a visibly
C 程序，
C program,
它模拟
um that simulates or emulates a
RISC-V 处理器。
RISC-V processor.
你可以在这里看到，
You can see here in
-kernel 标志实际上
the "-kernel" flag actually
传递给内核。
passes the kernel.
由于要在 QEMU 内部
As the program to
运行的程序，
be run inside of QEMU,
内核指定
and QEMU and the kernel
任何程序的
agreed basically the starting place,
起始点都是
any program is to
地址 80000 。
address 80000.
我们看到在 QEMU
And we see that we passed
中传递了几个标志，
a couple of flags in QEMU,
它们只是，
it's just you know,
是虚拟机
um, that's an amount of
拥有的
memory that the machine does
内存量，
virtual machine has,
这个虚拟的 RISC-V 机器。
this virtual RISC-V machine.
它传入了许多，
um, it passes in how many,
当然
of course, there are
传给虚拟机，
passes in the machine,
包含文件 fs.img
the disk drive which contains
的磁盘驱动器。
the file fs.img.
所以基本上
And so basically a bunch of
有一堆东西设置，
things are sort of set up
让 QEMU 表现得
to make QEMU behave
像一台真正的计算机。
like a real computer.
所以当你考虑 QEMU 的时候，
And so one way when you
一种方式是，
think about QEMU,
你不应该把它当作
you really should not think about
一个 C 程序，
it as a C program, really
你应该像下面
the way you should think about
这样考虑它。
it is as follows.
你应该把它想成是，
Um, you should think about it
像这样。
as, as this.
也就是一个真正的电路板，
Namely a real board,
嗯，
um, so,
比如说左边的，
for example the on the left
你知道这是
you know this is a
一个 RISC-V 电路板。
RISC-V board.
实际上这就是我
Um, actually the RISC-V board that
办公室里的 RISC-V 板，
sits in my office and you
你知道它可以
know it can boot more
引导 xv6 。
or less xv6.
所以当你
And so when you're running you
使用 kernel
know QEMU, with your kernel
运行 QEMU 的时候，应该认为它
used to, think about it that
是在这块板上运行的。
actually running it on this board.
我知道电路板
And I know the board has
有开关按钮，
been on off button,
这是 RISC-V
here's actually to
处理器的。
RISC-V processor.
你知道外设
Um, you know there's room
是有空间的，
for peripherals,
比如说有一个接口
for example one of these connectors
是以太网的接口。
is a connector for ethernet.
一个是 PCI 插槽，
Um, one is that PCI slots,
电路板上有一些 RAM 芯片，
yeah there's some ram chips on
我不太清楚
the board I don't exactly know
它们在哪里，
where they are,
但确实有。
but there are.
这是一种
Um, and so this is sort
物理硬件，
of a that's the physical hardware,
你实际编程的计算机，
the computer actually, actually you're programming
所以 xv6 管理着
so xv6 manages
这块电路板。
this board.
这就是你脑海中
Um, and that's the picture usually
通常会有的画面。
have in your head.
事实上，
And in fact if you zoom
如果你把它放大，
in you can find all the
你可以找到所有的文档，
documentation of what actually sits inside
关于它里面到底有什么。
of this.
在这个里面，
Um, and inside of this,
你知道这个 RISC-V
you know there's inside of
处理器的内部，
this RISC-V processor,
RISC-V 处理器
the schema for the
的模式
RISC-V processor is shown in
如图所示。
this picture here.
你知道，看这里，
Um, and you know see here,
有多个内核。
for example there are multiple cores.
事实上，
In fact,
四核，
four cores,
这有一个
um, you know there's a
二级缓存，
l2 cache,
有一个到 DRAM 的连接器。
um, there's a connector to dram.
你知道有很多种方式
Um, you know there's a bunch
可以连接到
of ways to connect to the
外部世界，所以
outside world, so you here
这里的 UART0 ， UART0 实际上
UART0 and UART0 was
一端连接到键盘，
actually connected on one end to
另一端连接到
the keyboard and to the other
显示器。
end to the display.
你知道
Um, and you know there are
有一些方法可以，
some ways to actually, um, get
让时钟走起来。稍后我将
clocks going. I'll talk about in
更详细地讨论，
much more detail later,
但这些组件
but these are all the components
基本上都是 xv6
that basically you know the
或你将修改的
xv6 or things that you will
与实际工作
be modifying to interact with the
交互的内容。
real hard work.
事实上，
And in fact the
QEMU 模拟的
computer system or the computer board
计算机系统与
that actually is emulated by QEMU
计算机板非常接近，
is pretty close,
除了没有 SiFive 制造的
you know minus some small details
这个特殊的计算机板的
to this particular computer board
一些小细节。
which is made by SiFive.
不幸的是，我不能
Um, unfortunately I can't tell you
告诉你真正的事情，
the real thing I just sit
我只是坐在办公室里，
in my office,
你知道的，而且
you know and I haven't been in
我从三月份以来就没有在我的办公室里了。
my office since March.
虽然收集了大量灰尘，
From collecting a lot of
但在运行 QEMU 时，
dust, but it's important to
记住这一点很重要，
keep in your head when
因为你基本上
you're running QEMU, you're
是在真正的硬件上运行。
running basically on real hardware.
只是碰巧能够
And just happens to be able
使用软件。
to software.
你们明白了吗？
Does that make sense?
[密码第二年]。
[Password second year].
让我再
So let me say a little
多说一点，
bit more about it,
那么 QEMU 模拟
so what does it mean for
RISC-V 处理器
QEMU to emulate
意味着什么。
RISC-V processor.
从字面上看，
Well, literally you know if you
如果你仔细想想，
think about it,
你知道，就像我说的，
you know as I said, QEMU
QEMU 是一个
simulate program it's an open
开源的 C 程序，
source C program,
它是一个很大的程序，
it's a big program,
你可以直接下载或者
you can actually just download it
克隆它。
or get clone it.
但是在深入 C 代码内部，
Um, but internally into C,
基本上是 for 循环，
is basically for loop,
一个无限的 for 循环。
an infinite for loop.
那除了读指令，
That does nothing else than
什么也不做。
read instruction.
RISC-V 指令基本上
RISC-V instruction basically reached four
达到了 4 个字节或 8 个字节，
byte or eight bytes,
基本上是查看
um, and basically looks at
该指令中的位
the bits in that instruction
并对其进行解码。
and decodes them.
弄清楚
Figures out what the op
操作码是什么。
code is.
我们看到了
And we saw back for some
一些指令，
of the instructions,
即 .asm 文件中这些指令的
the binary version of those instructions
二进制版本。
in the .asm file.
因此对指令进行解码，
So decodes the instruction,
例如，
so for example,
它可能会确定
maybe it will decide this is
这是一条 add 指令
an add instruction,
sub 指令，
sub instruction,
RISC-V sub 指令，
RISC-V sub instruction,
然后执行
and then basically it executes
该指令。
the instruction.
我是说软件。
I mean software.
你知道，
And you know that basically
这基本上就是它
is all what it does
对每个核心所做的一切，
for every core,
你知道，运行这个特定的循环。
you know runs this particular loop.
此外，在某种程度上，
And in addition sort of doing
执行此循环
this loop has to maintain some
必须保持某些状态，
states to maintain state for all
以维护所有寄存器的状态。
the registers.
所以它有
So it has C decoration for
类似于 x0 ，寄存器 0 ，
like x0, register 0,
x1 等的 C 修饰。
x1 etc.
所以基本上，
And so basically when it executes
当它执行指令时，例如，
instruction, for example,
指令就像，
the instruction is like, whatever
a0 ，1 到 7 ，
you know a0,
存储在 a0 中，
one to seven, and stored in
它需要常数 7 ，
a0, invisible it takes constant
加 1 后
seven one adds them up and
存入 a0 中。
sticks into a0.
7 的例子在这里面，
Examples for seven in it, and then
然后它得到了下一条指令，
it actually gets next instruction
它继续执行，继续执行。
and it keeps going, keeps going.
除了直观地模拟或
In addition to visually emulating or
正确地模拟
correctly all the imprivilege instructions,
所有非特权指令之外，
it also emulates all the
它还模拟所有特权指令。
privileged instructions.
这就是
So that is,
本质上 QEMU 所做的，
in essence, what QEMU does,
对你来说，
in, the best picture for
头脑中最好的图像是
you to have your head is
你在运行在真正的
the visible you're running on a
物理 RISC-V 处理器上。
real physical RISC-V processor.
就像你们已经拥有的那些，
Like the ones you have probably
你们中的许多人
you know many of you implemented
在 6.004 之后实现了一个。
one after 6.004.
关于这个，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
嗯，
Um, hi,
是的，我想知道它
yeah I was wondering if it
有没有硬件技巧，
does any hardware tricks,
比如指令重叠之类的。
so like overlapping instructions or anything.
嗯，
Um I know,
它是在下面的
um, it runs on a real
一个真实的进程上运行的，
process below it correctly when you
当你运行 QEMU 的时候，
run QEMU,
它可能是在运行在
it runs probably on an
x86 处理器上。
x86 processor.
x86处理器，做了
The x86 processor and does all
各种技巧比如流水线指令和
kinds of tricks to pipeline instructions
类似的事情，
and things like that right,
所以你对 QEMU 的看法是，
so the way you think about
只是一个 C 程序。
QEMU, just a C program.
理解了，
Makes sense,
谢谢。
thank you.
那么多线程呢，
What about multi threading so if
如果
the, the QEMU supports you
QEMU 支持四核，
said four cores or does it
或者它只支持一个，
only support one and it's in
在这种情况下，
that case,
它是否真的
does it have actually multiple threads
有多个线程在运行它。
running it.
是的，实际上
Yeah, so actually the QEMU that
我们在 Athena 上使用的 QEMU ，
we use on the Athena, and
可能是你
were probably the ones that you
下载的 QEMU ，
actually download,
它们在内部使用多线程，
um, they will use multiple threads
所以在内部使用它
internally so you internally use it
来获得并行性，
to get parallelism,
所以实际上，
so in fact,
这四个核心
these four cores that are being
正在被并行仿真。
emulated or being emulated in parallel.
我们稍后将在
And we'll see that in one
其中一个实验室看到，
of the labs later, how how
它是如何发挥作用的。
that plays out.
是的，所以
Yeah, so definitely there's a
在不同的核心之间
real parallelism going on between
肯定存在真正的并行。
the different cores.
好的，
Okay, um,
所以我要做一点，
so I'm gonna do a little
在 xv6 中看看，
bit of, walking through
来了解一下
xv6 to get a
它的结构是
little bit of sense,
怎么样的。
what the layout of the land is.
在后面的课程中，
Um in, in later lecture again
我们会讲得
we're going to go in much
更详细。
more detail.
所以我要
Um, so I'm gonna fire up
启动 QEMU ，
QEMU and um,
使用 gdb 支持，
with gdb supports, basic
基本的 QEMU 里面
QEMU has inside of it
有一个 gdb 服务器。
a gdb server.
嗯，它启动了，
Um, and so it started up
然后等待，
and then just wait,
你知道的，
you know for gdb
让 gdb 连接。
to connect.
为此，我从
To that I'm going to start
我的计算机开始，
here on my computer,
这是一个 risc64-linux-gnu-gdb 。
this is a risc64-linux-gnu-gdb.
一些你们的计算机
Um, some of your machines might
可能是 multi-arch 或类似的。
be multi arch or something else.
但是基本上
Um, but basically the gdb
是为 RISC-V 64
compiled for risc64,
编译的 gdb 。
RISC-V 64.
我将在入口处
And I'm going to set the
设置断点，
break point at entry because that's
因为这是我们知道
the first we know it has
它大概是
roughly the first instruction.
实际工作
That actually working is going to
会跳到的第一条指令。
jump to.
我设置了断点运行，
I set the break point run
它实际上不会
and basically, it doesn't actually break
准确地在 8000 处中断，
exactly at 8000
而是在 0a 处，
but at 0a and if we
如果我们看右边，
look here on the right we
我们会看到 0a 是，
see that 0a is,
读取
reading the
控制系统寄存器 mhartid
control system register
并将该值
mhartid and loading that value
加载到 a1 中。
into a1.
所以基本上 QEMU
And so basically QEMU simulates
模拟指令，
the instruction,
然后我们可以执行该指令，
then we can execute that instruction,
然后我们进入
then we go to the
下一条指令。
next instruction.
这个地址 8000
Um, in basically, this address 8000
基本上
it's just basically something
是指定的，你知道，
that was agreed on, you know
由 QEMU 告诉，
by QEMU or QEMU told,
基本上说，
you know basically says,
你想使用 QEMU
you want to use QEMU
的第一个指令，
the first instruction,
我们要跳到
we're going to jump to is
那个特定的位置。
at that particular location.
我们安排了
And we basically arranged for the
内核加载器。
kernel loader.
加载该程序的内核，
To load the kernel that
因此有一个
program so there's a file
kernel.ld 文件。
kernel.ld.
这基本上指定了
That basically specifies how the kernel
内核应该如何加载，
should be loaded,
你在这里可以看到，
and you see here that basically
内核将使用的第一个地址，
the first address that the kernel
实际上是
is going to use, is actually
你指定的特定地址，
that particular address,
QEMU 指定的。
the basic QEMU specified.
我们就是这样
This is how we get off
开始的。
the ground.
能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
好的，
Okay, um,
我们还看到，
we see also that here actually
在这里， gdb 实际上显示了
gdb shows the binary encoding of
指令的二进制编码。
the instructions.
所以我们可以看到，
And so we see that basically
我猜 csrr ，是一条，
I guess the csrr, is a,
是的，
um, yeah,
四字节指令，
four byte instruction and addi is
而 addi 是一条双字节指令。
a two byte instruction.
好的，我来看看，
Okay, I'm going to see, basically
实际上是
so actually starts basically starts at
从 entry.S 开始的。
entry.S .
没有页表，
Um, yeah with no paging with
没有隔离的，事实上
no isolation and in fact we're
我们是从[模式]开始的。
starting in [mode].
以独占方式
Exclusive jumps as quickly as
尽可能快地
possible to
跳转到内核模式或管理模式，
kernel mode or supervisor mode,
这在 RISC-V 中被调用，
that called in RISC-V, I'm just
我只是在 main 上
going to set a break point
设置一个断点，它实际上
at main which actually runs in
是在管理模式下运行的，
supervisor mode,
我将在那里运行。
I'm going to run there.
然后我就到了 main 的
And then I get to the
第一条指令。
first instruction of main. So,
那么，让我展示一下，这是 main ，
let me show this, here's main
嗯，
in,
我想在这种布局下
um, I'd like to run gdb
运行 gdb ，
in this layout,
split 模式。
split mode.
所以你可以在 gdb 中看到，
So you can see in gdb
以及下一条指令
actually and what the next instruction
正在被执行，
is being executed so you see,
在那个特定的指令处
there's a break point at that
有一个断点。
particular instruction.
因为只有一个 CPU
Um, since there's a run
运行 QEMU ，
QEMU with one CPU,
这使得 gdb
just makes it, gdb a
变得更容易一些，
little bit easier,
所以现在
so there's now only one
只有一个活动的内核。
core active.
QEMU 只模拟
QEMU emulates only one
一个内核，
single core and I can
我可以单步完成，
step through that,
所以我可以
so I can go through
执行下一条指令，
the next instruction and others
其他调用一个名为 consoleinit 的函数，
calls a function called console
该函数的功能与
init which does exactly
你想象的完全一样，
what you imagine it does
它实际设置了
it actually sets up the
控制台。
console.
一旦我们设置了
And so once we set up
控制台，
the console,
我们就可以向它打印了，
we can actually print to it
所以，
and so,
你们会看到，我们很快
you'll see in a second we'll
就会得到一条新的输出，
get a new line and will
并且会得到 xv6 引导。
get xv6 booting.
好的，
Okay so there's a whole bunch
有一大堆额外的，
of additional, um,
代码来设置东西，
code to set things up,
你知道有一个设置
you know there's a setting up
页面分配器，
the page allocator,
设置一个虚拟内存，
setting up a virtual memory, which
我们将在周三讨论，
we'll talk about on wednesday, loading
加载实际上开始打开分页，
actually starting turning paging on, which
这也是我在周三讨论的。
I also talk about on wednesday.
设置初始进程或者
Um, setting up the initial processes
设置进程表，
or setting the process table,
由于内核位置的使用
setting up code due to
而设置代码，
the use of the kernel position,
设置中断控制 plic ，
setting up the interrupt control
我们在讨论中断的时候
the plic, we'll talk about when
还会再谈。
we talk about interrupts.
但是这是一回事，
But this is one thing that,
我们主要
um, we're gonna be using to
使用中断来
basically talk to the disk or
访问磁盘或
talk to the
与控制台对话，
console using interrupts,
设置文件系统，
sets up the file system
分配缓冲区缓存，
allocates buffer cache initialize the
初始化索引节点缓存，初始化文件系统，
inode cache, initialize the file system
初始化磁盘。
initialize the disk.
基本上，一旦
And then basically once all sort
所有的事情都设置好了，
of things are set up,
你就知道当操作系统
you know when the operating system
运行的时候，
is running,
它将开始运行
it's going to start running the
第一个进程，这就是
first process and this is the
userinit 。
userinit.
这里有一点有趣的，
So there's a little bit of
所以我
interesting, so I'm going to go
转到 userinit，
to userinit,
稍等片刻，
um, for a second I'm going
我单步操作到那里。
to single step there.
在继续之前，
Um, before continue, any questions
有关于这个的问题吗？
about this?
是否存在
Is there a specific order in
需要调用设置函数的
which the set-up functions need to
特定顺序。
be called.
是的，有些函数，
Yes, some function,
一旦我们运行其他函数，
once we run after other functions
嗯，
and um,
它们比较特别，
they're in particular in there some
有些则无关紧要，
of them doesn't matter,
但是有几个，
but a few of them yeah
它们在其他函数后面运行
it's important that they run after
是很重要的。
other ones.
很好的问题。
Good point.
好的，
Okay, um,
让我转到，
let me go to,
userinit 。
um, so userinit.
基本上 userinit
And basically userinit there's
有一点胶水代码，
a little bit of glue code
组织代码利用了
organization code to take advantage of
所有通用的基础设施，
all the general infrastructure [decks] have
卡片组基本上
basically get the first process of
都得到了基础的第一个过程。
the ground.
你知道 xv6 需要
Um, you know xv6 needs
一些镜像，
some image,
我们还不能真正
we can't run the file system
运行文件系统。
really yet.
或者 exec ，
Um, or do exec,
所以 xv6 服务
um, and so xv6 server
小程序开始运行，
small little program to get off
那个小程序是
the ground and that small little
初始化代码。
program is init code.
该程序的二进制版本
And the binary version of that
实际上静态地链接或声明
program is actually linked or declared
到内核中，并且代码
statically into the kernel and the
对应于这个
fact that code corresponds
特定的用户程序。
to this particular user program.
这是一个
It's a, it's a little
用汇编语言编写的小程序，
program written in assembly and basically
基本上是这样做的，
it does, loads the address in it
把里面的地址加载到 a0 中，
into a0, it loads
把 argv 的地址加载到 a1 中。
the address of argv into a1.
然后它将
And then it loads the number
SYS_exec 的号码
for this SYS_exec in
加载到 a7 中，
to a7 and then look
然后这里，它调用 ecall 。
at the here, that calls ecall.
基本上，它所做的
So basically what it does is
就是运行三条指令，
running three instructions and then running
然后运行第四条指令，
the fourth instructions which basically transfer
将控制权
back control to the,
转移回操作系统，
back control to the operating system,
所以如果我在 syscall 中
so generally if I set a
设置一个断点。
break point in syscall.
现在继续运行，
Um, and now keep running then
那么基本上 userinit，
basically you know userinit,
你知道将创建初始进程，
you know will create the initial
返回到用户空间
process return to user space run
运行屏幕指令。
the screen instructions.
或者对于指令，
Or for instruction,
回到
and basically come back into
内核空间。
kernel space.
假设这是
So imagine this is the first
xv6 中任何用户应用程序
system call that any user application
运行的第一个系统调用，
in xv6 runs,
那么让我们看看会发生什么。
so let's see what happens.
如果我是对的。
If I'm right.
我们继续，
So we're continue and we
我们到达了 syscall 。
actually got to syscall.
所以我们可以
Um, so we can syscall we
查看它，
can look at it it's a
这是底部的一个函数。
function at the bottom.
现在我们回到内核空间，
And so we're back into kernel
我们看看，
space now and we're going to
看看在 syscall 中
walk through and see actually what
到底发生了什么，
happens exactly in
我也会继续
syscall, also I'm gonna single
单步运行。
step a little bit.
它看起来是关于内核的，
Um, it looks about the kernel,
它里面的进程，
the processes within it,
你知道的，
you know that pulls out the
取出系统调用号，
system call number,
我们现在可以
that's used so we can now
打印 num 了。
print num.
让我们看看这是 7 。
And let's see that's seven.
如果我们看一下
And if we look at which,
哪一个，
user when kernel
当内核 syscall.h 。
syscall.h .
它声明了所有的系统调用号，
That declares all the system call
我们看到 7 是
numbers and we see seven that
SYS_exec 。
is indeed SYS_exec.
基本上，这会告诉
And so basically this tells
内核一些
the kernel that you know
用户应用程序
some user application
调用了 ecall 指令，
called ecall instruction and
并且意图调用
with the intention of calling this
该系统调用，
system call for,
意图运行 exec
with the intention of running the
系统调用。
exec system call.
我们可以再
And so we can single step
往前走一步，
a little bit further um,
我们来看看下一步，
we go through the next thing,
这是执行系统调用的
this is the line that executes
那一行，
a system call,
所以让我们转到那里。
so let's go there.
你可以看到，
And you see that basically the
数字基本上是用来索引数组的，
number is used to index into
数组是一串
an array and arrays as a
函数指针。
bunch of function pointers.
你知道，大概 sys
And presumably, the sys entry,
入口指向
you know points to the sys
sys exec 函数，
exec function,
所以我们将单步
so we're going to single step
进入这一步。
into this.
嗯，
And, um,
我们实际上是在
we see that we're actually at
sys exec 。
the sys exec.
嗯，所以这是在
Um, so this is in
sys 文件里。
sys file.
我们可以把它
Now we can move it a
移动得更多一点，窗口更大一些。
little bit more and bigger window.
我们可以在这里
And we basically see
看到系统调用。
here, the system call.
你看到的第一件事
Um, and the first thing that
实际上是从
you see actually it actually gets
用户空间获取参数，
arguments from user space so it
所以它获得了路径名。
gets the path name.
我们想跳得
So we want jump a little
更远一点。
bit further.
memset ，
memset, um,
嗯，
um,
基本上是为参数分配空间，
basically allocates space for arguments,
你知道将所有参数
you know copys all the arguments
从用户空间复制到内核空间，
from user space to kernel space,
我们将在几周内
we'll look down in great amount
详细介绍，
of detail in a couple weeks
所以现在
so don't worry about it too
不要太担心。
much yet.
但是基本上
But basically there's some code to
有一些代码
move arguments user space to
可以将参数从用户空间移动到内核空间，
kernel space,
你知道，从内核，
you know from the kernel, from
从用户地址空间到
the user address space to kernel
内核地址空间。
address space.
如果我们
And if we now look
现在看 path ，
at path,
你就有可以打印出 path 。
you can print the path hopefully.
你会看到，
You'll see actually that you
实际上这是一个字符串，
know that is a string
你会看到，基本上，
and you'll see that basically
这个小的内部代码程序
what that little inner code
所做的，
program does is trying to
就是试图
exex you know the init
执行 init 程序。
program.
这是另一个程序，
Which is yet another program,
我们来
so let's look at that for
看一下，
a second just to see
看看是什么。
what that is.
这里我们有 init ，
So here we have init
init 设置了
and init basically
一些用于用户空间的东西，
sets up a couple things
它向控制台打开，
use for user space,
控制台的
it opens to console, the file
文件描述符，
descriptor for the console, dup it
重复几次。
a couple times.
调用 fork ，
Calls fork and basically the first
它实际做的第一件事
thing it does actually it starts
就是创建一个新进程。
to create a new process.
我们将 exec shell ，
And we'll exec the shell and
所以这最终
so this will in the end
会导致 shell 运行。
result as the shell being run.
例如，如果
So, for example if I would
我要继续，我可能会再次中断，
continue I probably break again,
比如 exec ，
it says exec,
如果我查看参数，
and if I look at the
我会发现实际上
arguments I will see that actually
正在调用 exec 系统调用
the exec system call is being
来执行 shell 。
called to execs the shell.
一旦你 exec shell ，
And once you exec the shell,
你知道，
you know,
让我们这样做，
let's do that,
然后我们会做更多的
then we'll do a couple more
系统调用，在某个时刻，
system calls and at some point
你会看到这一点。
you'll see that.
我要继续，然后
I'm gonna do continue then basically
shell 就开始运行了。
the shell starts running.
所以它给了你
So it gives you a little
一点感觉，
bit of sense,
知道 xv6 实际上是
you know actually how xv6
如何开始的，
gets off the ground, the
第一个 shell 出口是如何运行的，
first shell exit gets run and
我们看到了
we saw this sort of a
关于第一个系统调用
little bit of an overview about
实际发生时
how the first when the first
第一个出口是如何发生的。
system call actually happened.
我们还没有真正了解
We haven't really looked at the
这些系统调用的潜水机制
dive machinery for these system calls
如何进入和
how to get in and out
离开内核，
of the kernel,
我们将在
we're going to talk about it
几周或
in a couple weeks or two
两周的课程中
weeks in lecture, in great
详细讨论这一点，
amount of detail,
但这已经足够
but this is sort of
让你们了解
enough for you to understand
如何实际做
actually how to do the
syscall 实验了，
syscall lab, you know that
我们这周布置的实验。
we assigned for this week.
那么这些
Um, and so these are
就是你们
the pieces that you will
将要互动的。
be interacting with.
在我结束之前有什么问题吗，
Any questions before I wrap up,
因为我们快没时间了。
because we're almost out of time.
你可以随意提问。
You're free to fire away.
我们要做什么
Are we going to do anything
关于网络的
with, um, networks are like networking
实验吗？
and labs?
是的，最后一个实验是
Yes, the last lab is
实现网络驱动程序。
you implement a network driver.
因此，你将编写与
And so you will write the
硬件交互的代码，
code that interacts with the hardware
你必须操作
you have to manipulate the
网络驱动程序或
register for the network driver or
网卡的寄存器。
a network card.
它将你连接到
Um that basically connects you to
这个 RISC-V 板，
this RISC-V board, you know
你看到的是一个块，
you saw that was a block
基本上是插入以太网控制器，
basically to plugin an ethernet control,
一根电缆，
a cable so there's an
有一块以太网卡。
ethernet card.
因此，你将对该卡
And so you're gonna be programming
进行编程，实际上你将
that card and you're gonna actually
通过互联网发送一些数据包。
send some packets across the Internet.
太好了，谢谢。
Great, thanks. Yeah,
是的，这是最后一个实验室。
it's the last lab.
还有其他问题吗。
Any other questions.
我认为是
We're gonna let me wrap up
对 syscall 实验
here I think the syscall
初步熟悉，
lab itself,
因为我们不会
um because we're not really going
讲太多细节，
great amount of detail,
希望不会太糟糕，
hopefully shouldn't be too bad,
可能比 util 实验
might be easier than
简单。
the util lab.
然而，下一个实验
Labs, next lab,
可能会更困难，
however might be more difficult,
所以总是很难把所有
so it's always hard to get
这些实验都做好，
all these labs right,
但 syscall 实验
but syscall lab hopefully it shouldn't
希望它不会太难，
be too difficult,
但请不要等到
but please don't start don't
前一天晚上
wait until the night before
才开始，
get going early,
这样如果你运行的是一些晦涩难懂的 bug ，
so that if you're running some
我们可以
obscure bug that we can actually
真正帮助你，确保你的程序
help you out and make sure
在其中工作。
that your program works in it.
到此为止，
With that,
我要退出了，
um, I'll sign off and I'll
周三见。
see you in Wednesday.